<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A balm to heal religions wounds applied in a serious advice to sober-minded Christians that love the truth, and are well-wishers to reformation : in answer to The pulpit guard routed, lately set forth by one Thomas Collier ... / by Richard Saunders ...</title>
            <author>Saunders, Richard, d. 1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 239 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S755A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42466</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282011</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36282011</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150263</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94219)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150263)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2238:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A balm to heal religions wounds applied in a serious advice to sober-minded Christians that love the truth, and are well-wishers to reformation : in answer to The pulpit guard routed, lately set forth by one Thomas Collier ... / by Richard Saunders ...</title>
                  <author>Saunders, Richard, d. 1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 175, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Simmons for William Adderton, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, tightly bound, and with print show-through; p. 11-14 lacking. Best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Collier, Thomas. --  Pulpit guard routed.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Pulpit guard routed.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150263:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BALM TO HEAL RELIGIONS WOUNDS, Applied in a ſerious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to ſober-minded Chriſtians that love the Truth, and are well-wiſhers to Reformation.</p>
            <p>IN ANSWER To the <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPIT G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARD RO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TED,</hi> lately ſet forth by one <hi>Thomas Collier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this ſmall Treatiſe you ſhall finde divers corrupt Principles of this <hi>Collier</hi> plainly confuted. His Ignorance fully laid open. Many Scriptures cleard from his corrupt gloſſes. Severall Queſtions handled touching; <hi>The Miniſtry. Infant-Baptiſm. Pardon of Sin. Extraordinary Revelations. Humane Learning. The Outward Call of the Miniſters of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> RICHARD SAUNDERS, Miniſter of the Goſpel for the Church of Chriſt in <hi>Kentiſhbeer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Simmons,</hi> for <hi>William Adderton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the three Golden <hi>Falcons</hi> in <hi>Duck lane,</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150263:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150263:2"/>
            <head>To the VVorſhipfull JOHN TYRLING, Eſquire, One of the Juſtices of the Peace for the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> my Dear Uncle.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Grace and Peace, &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Is not long ſince, I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from your hand that Pamphlet, intituled, <hi>The Pulpit Guard Routed,</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating mine intentions to write an Antidote againſt the poyſon of it: And ſeeing you gave me ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to the worke, as you well remember, I could not thinke upon a fitter Patron to commend the ſame unto then your ſelfe: which I the rather have done, that I might have an opportunity more publiquely to acknowledge how much I am bound to you, for thoſe reall expreſſions of kindneſſe and
<pb facs="tcp:150263:3"/>love which I have ever had from you; eſpecially ſince I have had ſome relation to you, which indeed have much tranſcended my deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings. Tis the leaſt I could doe to mention this, though I know tis more pleaſing to you to beſtow fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and reſpect, then to heare of the ſame againe to your praiſe.</p>
            <p>But I muſt take leave to be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which is the leaſt you can, and, I beleeve, the moſt you doe, expect from any.</p>
            <p>I need not excuſe my ſelfe to you, for that I have trimd this Diſcourſe no better, that it might be more worthy of your acceptance; ſeeing I know you judge not of things by their outſide, but have reſpect more to their ſubſtance, then to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities. When Satan is ſo buſie (as now) there is no time to ſtick at nicities.</p>
            <p>The Lord continue to hold up your ſpirit in his own work. I know you have appeared for the ſervice of your Country, in your place
<pb facs="tcp:150263:3"/>(while others ſhifted their necks off the yoke) even to the waſting of your naturall ſtrength: but God will make this up again to you ſome other way. Theſe are times where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in much work lies upon the hands of ſuch as are faithfull. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing loſt by ſticking cloſe to the intereſt of Chriſt. Chriſtians have a good Maſter, and (which is a choice incouragement) the work of God is ſuch a worke, as will improve, and crowne it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>I beleeve the inſolency of ſome that pretend gifts to juſtle out the Miniſtry of Chriſt, yea and his truth too, doth ſomewhat damp your joy you take in the proſperous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the affairs of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: But, <hi>Dabit Deus huic quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 12.</note> 
               <hi>finem: Theſe clouds without water</hi> will ſoon be blowne over: They are as bubbles that will break with a light touch.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> In quietus, turbulentus, <hi>unſetled, wavering.</hi> Legh. Sac. Crit.</note> 
               <hi>For yet a little while</hi> (ſayes <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 37.10.) <hi>and the wicked</hi> [Heb: the turbulent, wavering, or unſteddy] <hi>ſhall not be, yea thou ſhalt
<pb facs="tcp:150263:4"/>diligently conſider his place, and it ſhall not be.</hi> In the interim let us fix our thoughts upon an immutable God. <hi>Let Patience have her perfect worke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.4.</note> and we ſhall be <hi>perfect, entire, and wanting nothing.</hi> A taxie in a wiſe Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth can never be long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liv'd. But what mean I keeping you from the Diſcourſe enſuing? You will ſee there this tottering wall is falling; but two poſts to keep it from the ground, Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Confidence, the one rots, the other breakes ſuddenly of it ſelfe. <hi>Praevalebit veritas, Truth will out-live its enemies,</hi> though ſome enemies of truth may out-live us here in the fleſh. Beeing eyed with a ſpirituall underſtanding we may ſee through all theſe thick Clouds, which that we may be able to doe, is the conſtant, and hearty pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your greatly-obliged Nephew: devoted to your, and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſervice in the Goſpel, <hi>RICHARD SAUNDERS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150263:4"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N unpoliſhed Peice is here put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thine hand, that which (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) coſt me more time to write it out faire for the Preſſe, then to compoſe it. I was pained within me till I had ſet it going, that it might come ſpeedily to thine hand, and leaſt any ſoule ſhould be enſnared firſt by that dangerous Pamphlet which I anſwer. Some foure or five weeks I laboured hard in compoſing the following Diſcourſe, and as many in writing it out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for publique view. If thou blame mee for not taking more time. I anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I met not with much in mine adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries Booke, that had any difficulty in it to hold me long.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Twas my tender reſpect to thy good that ſpurred me on ſo faſt, and if I looſe credit in any meaſure, by ſetting forth my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions in no better a dreſſe, thou mayeſt well pardon me, <hi>for if I have plaid the fool it is for thy ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150263:5"/>
But thirdly, Such as it is, if thou be not too curious, I hope it will appeare ſufficient as to that which twas intended for, viz. a confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mine Antagoniſt.</p>
            <p>If my Diſcourſe chance to come into the hand of a learned, and judicious Reader; though ſuch a one it may be may finde in it, that, which may make him judge it not loſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to reade it over; yet I muſt ſay my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect was not to ſuch in writing this, there beeing nothing in the Book I anſwer, that is like to paſſe for ſound reaſon with diſcerning ſpirits. My reſpect was to weak Chriſtians, Babes in Chriſt, and ſuch as are ready to ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at every ſtraw, upon whom the boldneſſe and confidence of the Collier may prevaile too farre, eſpecially while he covers over his deſigne with pretenſions to the honour of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>If thou findeſt any inclination in thy ſelfe to cenſure me for the tartneſſe of ſome of mine expreſſions, conſult ſeriouſly with thine owne heart, whether the confidence, and yet weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and groſſe abſurdities, of mine adverſary doth not give juſt reaſon. I was never (if I may ſpeak ſo of my ſelfe) a man of a bitter, or rigid ſpirit in my life, eſpecially againſt any that I could looke upon as Godly. And truely, if I could have ſeen any Characters of an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Chriſtian Spirit in the <hi>Pulpit Guard
<pb facs="tcp:150263:5"/>Routed,</hi> I ſhould not have uſed altogether ſuch language as now I am enforced to doe. But it may be if thou ſeriouſly commune with thine owne heart, inſteed of cenſuring me, thou wilt finde ground to judge thy ſelfe, for not beeing ſufficiently ſenſible of Gods diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, occaſioned by the venting of ſuch corrupt principles as I engage againſt.</p>
            <p>If thou wonder (as it may be ſome will) to ſee me appearing in ſuch Controverſies as ſome of theſe are, who have lately appeared as publiquely in a Diſcourſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> In a ſhort Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the lawfulneſſe of ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the preſent Power.</note> wherein I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered my ſelfe contrary minded to a great number of thoſe, I now plead for.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing I differ, in ſome matters of Church-Diſcipline, and order, from many of my Brethren. I muſt tell thee,</p>
            <p>Firſt, I love to ſpeake truth (when neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty calls for it) what ever they be I ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I cannot endure to be reputed a favourer of ſuch corruptions as my ſoule ever abhorred, which I ſhould be, if I ſhould hold my peace in the things hereafter diſcourſed of.</p>
            <p>I have freely encouraged Chriſtians to the uſe of their Liberty in edifying one another, in the uſe of their gifts: and how many have ſuſpected that I countenanced the confuſed Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty that is pleaded for by theh <hi>Pulpit Guard Routed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150263:6"/>
I have ſcrupled the baptiſing all infants, not judging but that all Church-Members in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are to be baptiſed, but ſeeing tis evident, that all among us are not ſuch as may be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced as Church-Members in this time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation endeavoured, all infants are not to be baptiſed: and upon this account I have, for a ſeaſon, ſuſpended the diſpenſing of that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to any, untill I can forme thoſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that have hearts to ſubmit unto the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of Chriſt into a body, according to Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall rule. And how many upon this account have thought me a friend to <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding my profeſſion to the contrary? When as I profeſſe tis not, but that I have ever owned Baptiſme of infants to be an Ordinance of Chriſt. And my ſuſpending the uſe of it, is,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe I judge it meet that thoſe, that enjoy Church-priviledges, either for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or Children, ſhould be accountable to the Church for their walking: which cannot well be, unleſſe there be a new-forming of Church-Societies, for preſent altogether without forme, order, or power.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe I am afraid, if I ſhould doe otherwiſe, what I build with one hand, I ſhould pull downe with the other, in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Church-Reformation.</p>
            <p>Now though I have ſufficiently (though not ſo publiquely as now) clear'd my ſelfe of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:150263:6"/>ſuſpitions, yet they made me ſomewhat the more willing to this undertaking.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I appeared alſo in this Diſcourſe the rather, becauſe it may be knowne that all that are for the preſent Power, are not (as ſome ſuſpect) favourers of theſe corruptions. I thinke I have appeared before, in, and after the change of affairs in this Land, as far as moſt of my Station, and I cannot be are the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour is done to the Noble Patriots of our Country by the ſecret whiſperings of theſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant Seducers, that ſpeak as if they were ſent by Authority, and Patronizd by it. Yea ſome of them (as I heard) had the boldneſſe to give out (when debate was touching a new Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative) that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſhould be the men that ſhould chooſe it. Twere good the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of ſuch fellows were curb'd. Such things trouble many honeſt hearts, not that they can beleeve ſuch toyes, but becauſe there is no check given to ſuch perſons. Among others this <hi>Collier</hi> I write againſt, deſerves to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: who can not be contented to ſet himſelfe againſt <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Chriſt, but alſo like a man of a ſeditious ſpirit, muſt jear at <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Parliament</hi> too.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Reader, I cannot be ſo prudent as to let Truth ſuffer by holding my peace, when my ſpeaking may diſpleaſe men. Tis true there may be a time when ſome Truths may not be
<pb facs="tcp:150263:7"/>fit to be publiſhed. But I promiſe thee; if God make knowne to me any thing further where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may doe the Church of Chriſt any ſervice, I ſhall not impriſon the Truth in me: And though in this learned, and knowing age, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſo many things are written by thoſe, with whom I am not worthy to be named, there is little reaſon to expect me much in print, yet ſhall I to my power, in my place, labour the promoting of the intereſt of truth, To which end I deſire thee to improve what intereſt thou haſt at the throne of Grace for me, and I ſhall remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>To truth, and peace: Chriſtian liberty, and order; an hearty well-wiſher.</hi> R. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150263:7"/>
            <head>A <hi>BALME</hi> To Heale Religions Wounds: In anſwer to the <hi>Pulpit-Guard Routed.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Proeme ſhewing the grounds of writing this Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be much wondred why I ſhould ſet pen to paper, to write an Anſwer to that railing Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet which is come out into the World under the name of the <hi>Pulpit Guard Routed,</hi> eſpecially ſeeing there is another (abler for the work) more properly and directly concerned in it. I muſt tell you it is no pleaſure to me to be contending about queſtions and controverſies, which engender ſtrife. I could wiſh (if the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God thought it fit) that there were no occaſion of ſuch a thing given,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150263:8"/>nor any neceſſity lying upon thoſe, that deſire rather to be imployed about more ſweet and ſavoury ſtudies, to turn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſuch unpleaſant work: But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that according to the Preacher, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.3. <hi>There is a time to breake downe, as well as a time to build up;</hi> I find God calling us now forth (as we are able) to both. Not only to building up, and repairing Gods ſpirituall fabrick in his Saints (which is our delightfull work) but to pull down thoſe dangerous ſtructures of hay, and ſtubble, which men of corrupt minds en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to raiſe up.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly; The reaſons why I (who am leſſe concerned in this buſineſſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did yet interpoſe in it, are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I am ſomewhat doubtfull whether M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hall</hi> (whoſe Book 'tis that this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Pamphlet pretends to anſwer) may have any purpoſe to make reply, in regard 1. It is ſo ſcurrilous, and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers ſo abſurd and impertinent. 2. The danger that may come of this Book, by corrupting the minds of weake and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteady people, may not be ſo viſible t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him, as to me, who live in and near thoſe parts, where the Author of it ha's mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> influence: and therefore I may ſee mor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reaſon why his Book ſhould not go without an Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150263:8"/>
2. The Author of this <hi>Pulpit Guard Routed,</hi> hath endeavoured to ſcatter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad his Books in this Countrey, unto the great danger of enſnaring many poor ſouls, whom the relation of neighbour-hood makes me more tender of then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Seeing his deſigne is chiefly promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in theſe parts, it may be, a word from me in theſe parts where I am known, may be more prevalent then an anſwer from a Stranger, though the buſines be better managed by him; yea, and what I ſhall write may take much the better abroad too, among them whoſe eſtabliſhment and information I chiefly aim at, while they ſee my judgement, wherein I goe ſo far to meet all well-wiſhers to reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as the Truth will give me leave; as thou mayeſt ſee in part in mine <hi>Epiſtle to the Reader:</hi> where thou haft alſo a further account of the ground of mine underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this work.</p>
               <p>Upon theſe Reaſons I have been enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to run the hazard of being cenſured as medling in other mens matters: though it be plain enough, that every honeſt ſoul is herein concerned, while the honour of Jeſus Chriſt, and of the Truth lies at ſtake.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150263:9"/>
If I deal very roundly with mine (and yet not mine ſo much as the Truths) Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, I may be excuſed, for that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe poſſibly come up to a full diſcovery of the Ignorance of that <hi>Rout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> it being wrapt up in ſuch wonderfull impudence.</p>
               <p>It is a true Proverb, <hi>Audax inſeitia, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance is bold:</hi> and truly I muſt ſay I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw ignorance growne ſo impudent and ſhameleſſe in my life. 'Tis ſtrange that a man ſhould write and print ſuch abſurd, weak, impertinent things, with ſo much confidence and diſdaine, trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing over Arguments as ignorant, and invalid, which he anſwers only with boldnes, and confident dictates of his owne braine, as you will ſee anon: you may perceive his plot is laid only to gain upon the humours of ſuch, as are more taken with words then things: and are ſwayed more by the confidence of an aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then the reaſon of it. Truly were it not that I find ſome that know not how to judge of the ſtrength of an Argument, or of the fallacious jugling of men of corrupt minds, and principles; but are apt to think there muſt needs be ſome ſtrength in that, which is boldly aſſerted by ſuch as have a viſour of Religion on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150263:9"/>their faces, and Scripture phraſes in their mouths; I ſhould not have thought that any paſſage in all his Book deſerved the credit of an Anſwer. Ah! but mine heart is moved toward poor weak ſouls for whom this ſnare is layd: 'tis not given to all to dive into the myſtery of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that ſome diſorderly ſpirits advance. Beloved Souls, you that love Jeſus Chriſt, mine heart is troubled for you, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you of theſe parts, whom the relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of neighbour-hood makes more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to me: I can gladly expoſe my ſelfe to the cenſures of men for your ſake, that your faith be not corrupted, nor your ſouls caught in a ſnare. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let mine advice from the Lord have place with you. Let your hearts with mine debate a little, and that ſeriouſly, as in the preſence of the great ſearcher of hearts, before whom both you and I muſt one day anſwer, about theſe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:150263:10"/>
               <head>Five ſerious Questions to be debated by modest Christians, in order to the diſcovery of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, and ſcope of the <hi>PULPIT GUARD ROUTED.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Queſt. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> WHether ſuch an uncharitable, cenſorious, proud, diſdainful, inveterate, calumniating ſpirit as viſibly works in this man, and others, <hi>ejuſdem farinae,</hi> of the ſame lump, does ever uſe to ſhew it ſelfe amongſt Chriſtians, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt godly perſons, much leſſe godly Miniſters? Ah! favour mine expreſſions, for I tell you.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. I cannot flatter ſuch corruptions, and corrupters with faire pleaſing ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, nor may I.</item>
                  <item>2. There are ſuch as are to be <hi>rebuked ſharply</hi> [or cuttingly] and all little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.13.</note> 
                     <hi>to make them ſound in the faith.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Is it poſſible (if it were true what theſe men would make you beleeve, that they are the men whom God ha's moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently appeared to, to open to them the myſteries of truth, and to call them ſorth to be Stewards of his manifold grace above others) Is it poſſible, I ſay,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150263:10"/>if it were ſo, that a ſpirit ſo contrary to the Goſpel, ſhould work ſo mightily in them? What, uſe all the expreſſions, and ſcrape up all the advantages they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that they may powre out contempt upon thoſe that are eminent Servants of Jeſus Chriſt, and yet pretend to be the crop of Gods family, as they would be thought to be? Surely I know not what entertainment that ſcurrilous language that is in that pamphlet hath where it comes, no doubt many phanſies are tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with it: but I profeſſe, my heart even trembled in reading ſome paſſages; yea, throughout the whole Book I can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finde any thing that ſpeaks much to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken my charity to beleeve, that there is ought of Chriſt in that heart, where ſuch ſtuffe was conceived.</p>
               <p>To omit thoſe diſdainful and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſpeeches, which he uſes againſt the man he pretends to anſwer; calling him, <hi>Ignorant, Fool, Knave, Enemy to truth, Of his father the Devil, Proud Phariſee,</hi> &amp;c. To omit theſe, which might admit of excuſe in part, for that they are againſt the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar adverſary he ha's to deal withall, but that he alſo heaps up moſt inſufferable reproach againſt the Miniſtry of <hi>England</hi> in generall, calling them, <hi>Antichriſtian, A
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150263:11"/>pack of cheaters and deluders, Carnall, Looſe, Baſe in Converſation, Theeves, Robbers, Wolves, Empty barrels making great ſounds, but having nothing but vanity and pride in them, Senſualiſts, Idlers often, ſuch as never knew what it is to live in a lawfull Calling, Whoſe God is their belly, Humaniſts.</hi> Several times, <hi>The baſtard brood of Rome. No Levites but baſtard ones. No Embaſſadours but ignorant ones. No Shepherds but kill them that are fed. Prieſtly Phariſees, Baſtard Tribe of Levites. Babyloniſh Diviners, Egyptian juglers, Limbs of the Devil,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Is not this brave language? Could you have worſe if you did rake the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt corners in Hell for it?</p>
               <p>Neither will this excuſe him that he ſayes in his Epiſtle to the Reader, that he doth <hi>anſwer a Fool according to his folly.</hi> For,
<list>
                     <item>1. I find no ſuch language in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Halls</hi> Book, nor doth he rebuke him (in his Anſwer) for any paſſage of that kind, except in ſpeaking againſt the thing he diſputes againſt: he doth not revile the perſons that are diſſenting from him: But,</item>
                     <item>2. If M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Hall</hi> hath been faulty (for I will not undertake to defend every ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of his) what ground is that for this man to be ſo inveterate <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150263:11"/>againſt the whole kinde, the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> without exception, or diſtinction? Is this the genius of a Chriſtian? Yea, is it not neer blaſphemy, to bring in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (as he does, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.5.) to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe his railing, and make Chriſt and his Apoſtles to be guilty with him in the ſame wickedneſſe?</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Neither doth he mend the matter when his Conſcience forces him to ſay (in his Epiſtle) that ſome of them may be godly. For though he doe leſſe then halfe grant this, ſaying <hi>[He is not deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the truth of it]</hi> which implies that he doth ſcarce beleeve that there are any godly, but hath onely ſo much hope of it, as keeps him from deſpairing that it is ſo; a moſt unchriſtian, ſatanicall cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: I beleeve every humble, gratious heart will judge it ſo, yet, I ſay, this mends not the matter that he almoſt half grants, that 'tis poſſible ſome of them may be godly, in that all along in his Diſcourſe, he reviles them with unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy termes, without putting any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. O yee Redeemed of the Lord, that are bid <hi>to try the ſpirits, whether they be of God,</hi> or no; examine the ſpirit of that Pamphleter: if it be the Spirit of Chriſt that moves in that puddle, I muſt profeſſe <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150263:12"/>ver knew yet what the Spirit of Chriſt meanes.</p>
               <p>Upon what grounds (think you) ſhould he,<note place="margin">Queſt. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> and men of the ſame temper and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with him, uſe ſuch bitterneſſe againſt the Miniſtry, and vent ſo much rancour with their pens &amp; tongues againſt them, when many hundreds of them are known to be very eminent and precious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and ſuch whoſe lives and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as alſo their doctrine, ſpeak them to be endeared to the Lord Jeſus? what can be the reaſon of this (I ſay) unleſſe it be becauſe they give a check to thoſe unſound principles (deſtructive to ſound doctrine and manners) that ſome of them endeavour to ſowe among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Here is the gall, here is the wring, elſe they are knowne to be ſound in the faith, godly in converſation, let your owne experiences (that read this) be witneſſes.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, diverſe of them have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied about the late wonderfull <hi>change</hi> in this <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> and have diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered themſelves oppoſite, ſome more, ſome leſſe, ſome nothing at all oppoſite, but yet unſatisfied in part: I could wiſh it had been otherwiſe, and that (if the Lord had pleaſed) they had ſeen things <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                     <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:150263:12"/>
Hath it not been an old trick of ſuch as have deſigned the ſhaking of the pillars of the Chriſtian Faith,<note place="margin">Queſt. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> firſt to begin with the faithfull Miniſters, to powre out con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon them? Did not <hi>Paul</hi> meet with ſuch in his time? What elſe made him write ſo much in defence of himſelfe, and the reſt of the faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt; in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. and ſeverall other places? I do not intend to plead for all thoſe that have gone under the name of Miniſters among us (no honeſt heart I think does) many have been for their lewdneſſe and malignancy, juſtly removed from their places; and many more do deſerve to be removed who are the reproach of the Goſpel. But to inveigh againſt Miniſters in generall (as <hi>The P. G. Routed</hi> doth) was it ever known to be the work of any but enemies to the faith? The Devil hath his<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
                  <hi>method</hi> of deceiving: obſerve it well, he firſt will caſt dirt in the face of the meſſengers of truth, and then of truth it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>All yee that love the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> my Chriſtian friends, neighbours, and country-men, let ſerious deliberate try-all goe before reſolution, in matters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to God. Can an humble ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150263:13"/>Chriſtian eaſily be perſwaded to ſwim againſt the ſtream of the moſt eminent and precious Saints of all Ages, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? I know the voice and word of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> ſhould be infinitely more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing with Chriſtians, then the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples even of the beſt men; But in things in controverſie and doubtfull, I ſhould make a great ſtand at the examples of ſuch; knowing that Chriſt ſpeaks to his people by preſidents as well as precepts. ſee <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Jude</hi> 7. &amp;c. wiſhing modeſt Chriſtians to weigh theſe things in their thoughts, I ſhall now open a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the vanity and childiſhneſſe of the anſwers and arguments of this ſame <hi>P. G. Routed,</hi> ſo far as it may make for the ſetling of their minds in the beliefe of the truths he endeavours to ſhake.</p>
               <p>His errours are many (though one mainly pleaded for) I ſhall in order in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the firmeneſſe of their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150263:13"/>
               <head>His Firſt Error.</head>
               <head type="sub">That the life of Miniſters and Schollars, educated in Schooles of learning is an idle life.</head>
               <p>THis you finde in the entrance of his diſcourſe: where pleading for the <hi>Nailer, Baker, &amp;c.</hi> as fit to make Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers he layes downe with much confidence (which is moſt of his ſtrength) this aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>That the life of Miniſters and Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers brought up in learning is an idle life:</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſuch <hi>Idlers</hi> and <hi>Drones, that never knew what it is to live lawfully in a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:</hi> with much more ſuch reproachfull Language.</p>
               <p>But how doth he make this good? Why, by a learned definition that he gives of a <hi>calling.</hi> ſayes he,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A calling is that in and by which men may in the ſweat of their face get their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note>
               </p>
               <p>O brave Definition of a <hi>Calling!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting a man that can call the moſt learned in the land ignorant, and ſimple. But let us examine it a little, if his defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition be good, then muſt it <hi>reciprocari cum ſuo definito,</hi> ſo as that it agree neither
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150263:14"/>to more things, nor to leſſe, then the thing defined doth: this is the conſtant law of a good definition.</p>
               <p>Now 1. Is every thing that a man may get his living by in the ſweat of his face a calling, <hi>i. e.</hi> a lawfull calling? (for ſuch he ſpeaks of) why then, he that ſweats at his robbing and ſtealing lives in a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full calling. It ſeemes he that would beat downe the calling of Miniſters, knowes how to ſet up another inſtead of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Is there no <hi>lawfull calling,</hi> but that whereby a man gets his living in the <hi>ſweat of his face?</hi> what will he ſay them of <hi>Magiſtrates, Juſtices</hi> of the <hi>Peace,</hi> men living by their eſtates, &amp; applying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the wel ordering of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey? what? becauſe they doe not <hi>worke with their hands,</hi> and ſweat at it, are they Idlers? Will he call the Parliament men Idlers, becauſe they ſpend their time in diſcourſing together, and debating the affairs of State, and doe not <hi>worke with their hands for their living?</hi> See this mans abſurdity. Yea, what will he ſay to Phyſicians? Doe not they live in a lawfull calling? yea, if his definition were good, 'twere time for him to go bid his <hi>Taylors, Button-makers, Semſters,</hi> and ſuch like, that ſeldome ſweat at their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150263:14"/>worke, eſpecially in winter ſeaſon, to finde out another way of living: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (although they were Preachers) yet are they not in a <hi>lawfull calling,</hi> by his rule. Ah! if theſe men that boaſt themſelves of abilities in a ſingular way from other men, to divide the word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, do ſo ſimply miſtake in giving definitions of things ſo familiar to the underſtandings of all men; what (think you) will they doe when they come to give you definitions of ſpirituall things? Moſt certaine it is that moſt of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous errours that are now on foot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, have ſprung out of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ignorance of ſuch men, who (though they can ſpeak pleaſing words that tickle the fancy, yet) are not able to give out any better accompt of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things they ſpeak of, then the <hi>Pulpit Guard Routed,</hi> doth here of a <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> the weakneſſe of which is very viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>But thirdly, Is it ſo, That none lives in a lawfull Calling, but he that <hi>workes with his hands,</hi> and gets his living in the ſweat of his face, what thinke you of <hi>Paul</hi> then? even of what he ſayes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Or I onely and Barnabas, have we not power to forbear working?</hi> Had <hi>Paul</hi> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150263:15"/>
                  <hi>Barnabas</hi> power to live Idelers? to live out of a lawfull calling; or did the reſt of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, who (as he intimates in this verſe, and affirme<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Verſe,</hi> 12.) did uſe this liberty of not working, did they I ſay live out of a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? were they Idlers?</p>
               <p>But by the way, let me from this plain Scripture frame this one Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove the Miniſtry of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel a diſtinct, lawfull calling.</p>
               <p>If a man may lawfully lay by all other callings, and apply himſelfe wholly to it, and live by it; then is it a diſtinct lawfull calling. That is clear from his owne words (which are moſt true) that <hi>No man may live out of a calling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But a man may lawfully lay by all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Callings, and apply himſelfe to the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the Goſpel, &amp; live by it; that i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> evident from the Text, where <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes <hi>He and Barnabas might leave working,</hi> verſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 6. That the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpel then, generally did, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. That they might, that twas fit they ſhould, yea, that God had <hi>ordained they ſhould live by it,</hi> ver. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.13, 14.</p>
               <p>Therefore the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the Goſpel, is a diſtinct lawfull <hi>calling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can any thing be more plain and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent then this?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150263:15"/>
But Fourthly, Is there no laboriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and pains-taking (for that Ile ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he may intend by ſweat) in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of Miniſters and Schollers? It ſeems he never knew what it is to ſtudy hard: It appears indeed by his Book. He is not acquainted with the labour of the minde, in getting downe to the bottom of things, and that's the reaſon he handles things ſo ſuperficially. But he addes,
<q>Breeding to School is proper to children when they can not labour to fit them for ſome calling.<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Very good, then, it ſeems,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> hee'l graunt that breeding children at School is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable. But it muſt not be (if you will beleeve him) any longer then <hi>while they cannot worke:</hi> And how long is that (pray) I would fain know, whether chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are not able to begin <hi>to work,</hi> as ſoon, or almoſt as ſoon, as they are able <hi>to goe to School:</hi> But it ſeems he would have them learne their <hi>A. B. C.</hi> and no more; for when they can <hi>labor,</hi> then they muſt away to that. Doe not you ſee how this mans ignorance opens it ſelfe in every line.</p>
               <p>But he grants they may goe to School, <hi>to fit them for ſome calling.</hi> Well then, then muſt they keep to the Schools till they are made as fit for the calling they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150263:16"/>as the Schools can make them; at leaſt till fit in ſome degree: and if ſo, then 1 His former aſſertion is falſe, that ſayes, <hi>They muſt keep the School onely while they cannot worke.</hi> 2 Then he that intends the calling of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> (which I proved before to be a diſtinct calling) muſt ſo long abide at the Schools, as is requiſite to make him an able <hi>Miniſter,</hi> ſo far as <hi>Schoole-learning</hi> may helpe him: and if ſo, then his maine poſition, here diſputed, is falſe too, that would make the life of a Scholer an idle, unjuſtifiable life. See how weakly this man contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts himſelfe and all in one page.<note place="margin">Object.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If he have ſo much ignorance <hi>(for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning had never any enemy but ignorance)</hi> as to ſay <hi>humane learning</hi> is no way uſefull to a Miniſter of the Goſpel; I ſhall uſe no other argument here,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> to refute him, but his own practice; why does he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times make uſe of the <hi>originall languages,</hi> to clear ſome Scriptures in his writings? I beleeve he is little acquainted with thoſe languages, but this that he is driven to enquire into them, that he may give out the true and full ſence of Scripture, it ſpeaks out the uſefulneſſe of the ſame to a Miniſter. More of this in its place: I ſhall ſtep forth unto his ſecond Errour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150263:16"/>
               <head>His Second Errour.</head>
               <head type="sub">That Infant Baptiſme is a Childiſh thing.</head>
               <p>THis he will owne for truth, and how will he make it good? he ſayes, <hi>'Tis childiſh,</hi> 1. <hi>As relating to the Subject,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>the child who is to be baptized, not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the uſe and end of it.</hi> 2 <hi>As relating to the Adminiſtrators, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the firſt, there lies a ſhreud ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection in his way,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> which he has ſo much ingenuity as faithfuly to ſet downe, but not ſo much wit as to anſwer with any ſence, as you ſhall ſee by and by. The Objection he layes downe thus.</p>
               <p>The Infants of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were as uncapable,<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> in (he would have written of) the underſtanding of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Circumciſion, as Infants are now of Baptiſme, yet they were by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God to be Circumciſed.</p>
               <p>'Tis a good objection indeed ſtarted,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> but how is it cleared? He gives a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold anſwer thus,</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Its truth that one part of Circumciſions Myſtery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> viz. <hi>the Circumciſion of the heart was as far from the capacity of Infants, as the myſtery of</hi> Baptiſme <hi>is now.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150263:17"/>
Very good,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> and what part of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions myſtery, pray, were Infants of eight dayes capable of underſtanding, if they underſtood not that? <hi>riſum teneamus &amp;c.</hi> who can but ſmile at ſuch an anſwer? as if Infants at eight dayes old did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand any part of the myſtery of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Circumciſion. I wonder he had not inform'd his Reader, what my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery ſuch were then capable of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, but what have you next.</p>
               <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>As Circumciſion was a type and ſigne in the fleſh, of Chriſt who was to come of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams ſeed, there was no ſuch capacity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</hi> His Reaſon follows, <hi>Becauſe it was a Jewiſh legall type, as all the reſt of their externall worſhip and Sacrifices were,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>O fine words to pleaſe Children,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the purpoſe!</p>
               <p n="1">1. Was there not required a ſpirituall underſtanding of the legal Ordinances, and Sacrifices then, as well as now o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Goſpel Ordinances? Doth this man thin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to perſwade any <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> or <hi>Orthodox Chriſtian,</hi> that the Iſraelites were not bound to ſee into the myſtery of their Ordinances, as we are into ours, without any reaſon? 'Tis true, they ſaw not ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150263:17"/>into the myſtery as we may, but that they did not at all underſtand, nor were bound to it, will eſtabliſh the dangerous doctrine of the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> that ſay they were juſtified by their legall Ordinances, without faith in Chriſt:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 15.11</note> and give the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle the lye, who ſays, that we are ſaved [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] even as they.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The knowledge of the myſtery of Circumciſion was not neceſſary to all that were circumciſed, to make them ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Circumciſion, he grants: well, and why is the knowledge of the myſtery of Baptiſme neceſſary to all that are to be Baptiſed, to make them capable of Baptiſme? If he had given a good reaſon for this, he had ſpoken ſomething to the purpoſe. He ſayes, <hi>Circumciſion was a type,</hi> ſo is Baptiſme alſo; whereas he ſayes 'twas <hi>Jewiſh and Legall,</hi> the ſence is, 'twas a type unto the Jews in times of the Law: and what is that to the buſineſſe? Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is a Type to Chriſtians under the Goſpel. They that have argued ſo long againſt Infant-Baptiſme, from this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that they are uncapable of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding its myſtery, could never yet give a reaſon, why the knowledge of the myſtery of Baptiſme is neceſſary to make a ſubject capable of it, when the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150263:18"/>of the myſtery of Circumciſion was not neceſſary to make the ſubject ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of it. Tell me what thing made In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants then capable of circumciſion, and then I'le tell thee (and thou mayeſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy ſelfe) that the ſame thing makes Infants capable of Baptiſme now. Their being ſuch as God had vouchſafed to take (together with their Parents) into Covenant with himſelfe, was that which made them capable of Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as appears in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8, 9, 10. where they are commanded <hi>Therefore</hi> to be Circumciſed, becauſe God had made a Covenant with them. Now the ſame thing makes Children of Beleevers now capable of Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>But his third Anſwer is of all the fitteſt for ſuch a man to give; it is this,</p>
               <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>There was a Command for that of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>O egregiouſly gifted Diſputant!<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> The Objection was if Infant-Baptiſme be childiſh, becauſe the ſubjects are Children, then Circumciſion was alſo Childiſh, which was commanded of God: to this he anſwers, <hi>Circumciſion was commanded</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Can you beleeve that the ſpirituall gifts that theſe men pretend to, are reall,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150263:18"/>when as in the utmoſt improvement of their gifts, they write ſuch non-ſence. If they write thus how do you think will they ſpeake, when they come to handle difficult matters, if they preach too with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meditation or ſtudy, as they boaſt? But whereas he ſayes, <hi>The command is that which gives a capacity,</hi> &amp;c. I ſhewed even now what it was that gave the Infants then a capacity of Circumciſion, from <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>The Command</hi> (as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Marſhall</hi> ſayes well) <hi>is the cauſe of the exiſtence of the duty, but the Covenant of grace is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to it.</hi> They were <hi>therefore</hi> circumciſed (as before) becauſe taken into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and ſo Church-members. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of this, let me away to his ſecond Reaſon, why Infant baptiſme is childiſh, which is as follows.</p>
               <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>It is Childiſh as relating to the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in not underſtanding the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But how doth he make that good?<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> why, you muſt take his word for it. He will call thouſands of able, judicious men ignorant, that by his confidence, you may think he is knowing and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent.</p>
               <p>His next corrupt Aſſertion borders
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150263:19"/>upon the ſame controverſie, touching In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-baptiſme: 'Tis this,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His third Error.</head>
               <head type="sub">That none muſt be baptiſed till they come to perfect Age.</head>
               <p>YOu have this defended by him, page 6. thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And is this ſuch a ſtrange thing with you who profeſſe your ſelfe a Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Was not Chriſt himſelfe Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at thirty years of age, the Eunuch by Philip,</hi> Acts 8? <hi>And thoſe of John,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Yea,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> and it may be ſtrange for all that, for what ſhadow of reaſon is there in it, why none muſt be baptiſed till they come to perfect Age? Is this good arguing, <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> &amp;c. were of perfect age when baptiſed, therefore none but men of perfect age muſt be baptiſed. Is not this as good an argument? When Chriſt gave the Supper, none were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but Apoſtles, therefore none but A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles may receive the Supper. If he ſay there be other Scriptures that give (not Apoſtles onely, but) all believers ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance unto the Supper; I anſwer, ſo there are other Scriptures that do autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize us to admit Children to baptiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150263:19"/>
Therefore he might have ſaved the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of anſwering the Objection, viz. <hi>That that was in the firſt Plantation of the Church,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For firſt, we need not fly thither, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe what he urges concludes not at all the thing aſſerted by him.</p>
               <p>He ſayes, <hi>None muſt be baptiſed but ſuch as are of perfect age,</hi> &amp;c. To prove it he urges, that ſome that were of perfect age were then baptiſed, which you know no way concludes that none but ſuch muſt.</p>
               <p>When any <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> can prove, that no Infants were baptiſed in the Apoſtles times, then it may be we ſhall make uſe of that which he brings in as an Objection, which if we doe, we muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat him to take a little better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Objection, and not miſtake it ſo ignorantly, as he ſeems to do in his Anſwer.</p>
               <p>For the thing urged in the Objection, is not, <hi>That there was one rule for them in the infancy, and another for us now.</hi> If he did underſtand ſenſe he would have ſeen it, but that the ſame Scripture rule that was then delivered to the Churches, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects us to a different courſe in gathering Churches, and in Churches gathered, which is very clear. So that none need
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150263:20"/>wonder why they heare of baptiſing growne perſons then, and Infants for the moſt part now. The reaſon is, becauſe though when our work is, as theirs was, to gather Churches, we baptiſe growne perſons upon their Profeſſion of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, as they did, and that moſt frequently: yet when the Church is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, we doe take in (according to Chriſts appointment) the Children of Beleevers in their infancy, the which I ſhall ſpeak more to by and by.</p>
               <p>Pretious Souls! you that love the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of the Lord Jeſus, I from mine heart owne the loweſt appearances of Chriſt in his people, I would not quench the ſmoaking flax for a world, nor dare I <hi>deſpiſe the day of ſmall things,</hi> in any: but when Ignorance doth ſo exalt it ſelfe, yea, even preſuming to call the Spirit of Chriſt its Father (as in theſe men) give me leave to be zealous for your ſakes, that you may (with the Church of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> Revel. 2.2.) <hi>Try them which ſay they are Apoſtles</hi> [or men ſent] <hi>and are not, and finde them lyars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that I may follow my valiant An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt (marching in the head of his victorious abſurdities and impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies) yet a little further, in what he ſays
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150263:20"/>more to this controverſie, page 8. I ſhall ſtep over one or two particulars, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the handling of them til afterwards, and apply my ſelfe to the finiſhing of what I intend about Paedo-baptiſme.</p>
               <p>He undertakes in the eigth page to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in reſpect of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther errour charged upon them, viz. that they deny all conſequences of Scripture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to which he ſayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You are miſtaken man in this too;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>they deny unneceſſary and untrue conſequences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I beleeve indeed this is the opinion on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the weakeſt and ſimpleſt of them;<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> and though the <hi>Pulpit Guard Routed</hi> be ignorant enough, yet it ſeems he is not ſo ignorant as to deny neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences drawne from Scripture. I ſhould have ſaid nothing to this, but for what followes. Sayes he,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your conſequences are ſuch as theſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>Baptiſme is come in the roome of Circumciſion, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants were circumciſed, therefore Infants muſt be baptiſed. The Apoſtles baptiſed houſholds, there might be Children; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Children may be baptiſed. Children were brought to Chriſt, therefore they may be baptiſed.</hi> Goodly conſequences.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:150263:21"/>
Are theſe the conſequences that are drawne out of Scripture to prove In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-baptiſme?<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Ha's not the <hi>Pulpit Guard Routed</hi> got a forehead of braffe, that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to tell the World ſuch a falſhood in Print?</p>
               <p>'Tis true, the firſt conſequence hath been made uſe of by ſome in the proof of Infant-baptiſme, and it is ſo plaine and unqueſtionable a conſequence, that if he had the leaſt graine of ſound reaſon in him, he could not have denied it. Mark it, he finds no fault with the Propoſition [Baptiſme comes in the roome of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion] but denies the conſequence that is drawne out of it. Now come hither Babes and Sucklings, and make good this againſt him; let all the world judge, whether if baptiſme come in the room of Circumciſion, this be not a good conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, Infants were circumciſed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Infants muſt be baptized. You will eaſily ſee his folly in this exception, if you note, he denies the conſequence, not the Propoſition on which 'tis ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>As for the other two conſequences, did ever any of thoſe that have written for Infant-baptiſme argue after that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? But I think this man never ſhewed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150263:21"/>ſo much affection to truth, or deſire of information, as to read the Arguments of thoſe that have writ ſoundly for it; if he had, he would have found other conſequences then ſuch as he mentions. Read the Arguments of <hi>Baxter, Marſhall, Homes, Featly,</hi> and others, or the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of any one of them, eſpecially <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Baxter,</hi> and ſee (Beloved Chriſtians) whether he goes not about to cheat you with his forgeries. But to the particular conſequences.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They argue (if he will have it ſo) baptiſme comes in the roome of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; Infants were circumciſed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Infants muſt be baptiſed. What hath he to ſay to this? ſayes he,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Law and circumciſion came by Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>but grace and truth, and Goſpel Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, came by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> See the ignorance of the great Text-man.</p>
               <p>Did circumciſion come by <hi>Moſes?</hi> Was it not inſtituted by God, in a command given to <hi>Abraham,</hi> long before <hi>Moſes</hi> was borne? But 'tis like he remembred that he read the ſtory of its inſtitution in one of the five books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and therefore thought <hi>Moſes</hi> to be the Inſtitutour of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150263:22"/>the ſame. A pittifull miſtake.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Ordinances that were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Moſes,</hi> were they not Chriſts Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, as well as thoſe appointed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel?</p>
               <p>But Thirdly, What is all this to the purpoſe? doth this at all weaken the conſequence? If <hi>Moſes,</hi> as Chriſts ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, did appoint Circumciſion, and Chriſt hath taken downe that, and ſet up another Ordinance of the ſame end, uſe, and ſpirituall ſignification in the ſteed of it, doth this hinder the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence aforeſaid? yea, doth it not above meaſure eſtabliſh it? — O moſt ſtrong conquering anſwers?</p>
               <p>But as to the Second conſequence: did ever any body (except ſuch a Diſputer as the <hi>P. G. Routed</hi> is) argue as he ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the next place, <hi>viz.</hi> Apoſtles bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Houſholds, there might be children, therefore children may be baptized.</p>
               <p>Did ever any of our Patrons of <hi>Paedo-Baptiſme,</hi> reaſon ſo?</p>
               <p>'Tis true ſome argue thus, The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles baptized whole houſholds, therefore 'tis probable there might be ſome children baptized then, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there are few families in which are not ſome children. None argue from
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150263:22"/>hence but for the probability of the fact, that tis probable ſome were baptized, and is not ſuch an inference tolerable?</p>
               <p>Whereas he ſayes, <hi>We muſt beleeve there were no children in thoſe families, or if any there, yet not Baptized, becauſe contrary to the knowne practiſe of the Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the ſimpleſt begging of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion that ever I met withall; For that is the thing in controverſie; to ſay there were no children baptized in thoſe fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. becauſe twas contrary to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Apoſtles to baptiſe Children, is <hi>idem per idem,</hi> a proving a thing by it ſelfe. Good Logick for—</p>
               <p>But if this will not paſſe (with the ordinary allowance of boldneſſe and confidence) you ſhall be accounted An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian, and willfully blind for it, be ſure.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Did ever any body argue, children were brought to Chriſt, therefore they may be baptiſed? I beleeve he hopes ſome will adventure to credit him, how falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoever he ſpeak or write. Surely this man would make you beleeve there are but very ſlender Arguments to prove Infant-baptiſme.</p>
               <p>But I'le tell you ſome of the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents that we draw from Scripture:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150263:23"/>they are ſuch as theſe.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that are Church-members an to be baptiſed.<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Some Infants are Church-members therefore ſome infants are to be baptiſed Againe.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that belong to the Kingdom of God are to be baptiſed.<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>But ſome Infants belong to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſome Infants are to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed. Againe.</p>
               <p>Such as are [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>holy</hi> by ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God,<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> are to be baptiſed.</p>
               <p>But ſome Infants are ſo. Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here are ſome of our conſequences t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prove Infant-baptiſme, that will make the ableſt <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> heart in <hi>England,</hi> ak<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to with ſtand. You have theſe, and many ſuch like Arguments enlarged upon, and cleared from all cavils, by ſeverall abl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men that have writ on this ſubject: but eſpecially by <hi>Mr. Baxter,</hi> in his book o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Infants Church-member ſhip;</hi> who, to my judgement, ha's done beſt of any on this controverſie.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe there ha's been ſo much ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken (and that ſo clearly and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cingly) by others, that for me to ſay any thing more, will be but to light a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150263:23"/>candle to the Sun. However I ſhall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a little with you about the firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, driving home that nail to the head, that he that can not read, or get larger Treatiſes, may have a ſufficient hint in this ſhort Tract, to enable him to ſtop the mouthes of ſuch, as ſhall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the truth here in diſpute. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſhall tread in the ſteps of acute and judicious M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Baxter</hi> for the moſt part.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That all Church-members are to be baptiſed, that I preſume none will deny, and therefore I ſhall take it for granted.</item>
                  <item>2. That ſome Infants are to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Church-members, I prove by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Argument, thus.</item>
               </list>
               <p>If by the mercifull gift, and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, not yet repealed, ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants were once to be admitted members of the viſible Church, then ſome Infants are to be ſo admitted ſtill.</p>
               <p>But by the mercifull gift and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, not yet repealed, ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants were once to be admitted members of the viſible Church.</p>
               <p>Therefore, They are ſo to be admitted ſtill.</p>
               <p>Examine this well. 1. That ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, by Gods gift and appointment, were
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150263:24"/>once admitted Church-members, I hope will be granted: they were members of the Church of the Jewes, that is beyond all diſpute. 2. God never repealed the grant of this priviledge to infants. If he ha's done it, let me know where. Can you think that a whole <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or kind of perſons ſhould be caſt out of the Church, and Scripture be ſilent about it? if the gift and grant of this priviledge be not repealed, then it remaines to infants ſtill.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall prove the Negative thus.</p>
               <p>If God hath revoked this mercifull grant and gift of Infants Church mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip, then it is either in mercy for their good, or in judgement for their hurt. But he hath neither revoked it in mercy for their good, nor in judgement for their hurt. This I ſhall prove in both parts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He hath not revoked it in judgement for their hurt: Becauſe many of them never broke Covenant with him, either in their owne perſons (being in their infancy uncapable of actuall ſinning) or in their Parents (by vertue of relation to whom, they had a ſtanding in the Church) many thouſands of whom were
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150263:24"/>beleevers in the Apoſtles times: Now God doth not caſt away them, that doe not caſt away him, for if he ſhould, then he himſelfe would be the Covenant-breaker, not man, which would be blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous to conceive. Therefore he ha's not revoked this gift of Church-member-ſhip as to infants, in judgement for their hurt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He hath not done it in mercy for their good; for then he would have granted to them ſome other mercy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of it: for it can be no mercy to take away a mercy (as Church-member-ſhip is) unleſſe to give a greater in the room. But there is no greater mercy gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to infants in ſtead of Church-member ſhip. If there be, then pray ſhew what it is.</p>
               <p>If any ſhould be ſo weak as to ſay,<note place="margin">Object.</note> That Chriſt comming in the fleſh is a greater mercy given in the roome of Church-member-ſhip. I anſwer.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. What a fond thing is it to conceive,<note place="margin">Anſw. <hi>1</hi>
                     </note> that Chriſt ſhould ſucceed Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhip, as a thing that was to be ended in him to any?</item>
                  <item>2. I would faine know, how infants (while infants) have Chriſt now, more
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150263:25"/>then infants had him then, when they were admitted Church-members.</item>
                  <item>3. The Church is the body of Chriſt, and is it not abſurd to ſay, that Chriſt ſhould break off infants from his body, that he comming in the fleſh may be a greater mercy to them? what is that but to be a greater mercy then himſelfe?</item>
               </list>
               <p>There is then no greater mercy given to infants in ſtead of Church-member-ſhip: therefore it is not taken away in mercy neither, and ſo by conſequence, not taken away at all.</p>
               <p>Which way will you ſhift from this Argument?<note place="margin">Object.</note> If you ſay the Church-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution (whereof infants were mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) is taken downe, and diſſolved, and a new ſet up, whereof infants are no members.</p>
               <p>I anſwer.<note place="margin">Anſwer. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 1. Many, yea moſt of the Jewes were broken off from the Church of God for their unbeliefe. So that ('tis true) that individuall Church may be ſaid to be diſſolved, even as alſo the Church of <hi>Smyrna, Thyatira, Laodicea,</hi> and the reſt of the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> (for the moſt part) are alſo diſſolved, and taken downe: but that the eſſence, and nature of the Church is altered, ſo as that theirs was not the ſame Church of God, that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150263:25"/>ours is now, is moſt contrary to plaine Scripture. As <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. where wee read, that all the change that was made, was, the <hi>breaking</hi> off of ſome branches of the Jewes, and the <hi>grafting</hi> in of ſome of the Gentiles into the ſame Olive. <hi>i. e.</hi> the ſame viſible Church. Againe, the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of the Gentiles is expreſt by a breaking downe of the partition wall, ſo making them one Church, by letting in the Gentiles into the ſame Church that the Jewes were of before. And when, in a Viſion, <hi>Peter</hi> was taught the doctrine of the Gentiles reception into the Church <hi>Acts</hi> 10. we finde 'twas not to be, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Jewes</hi> uncleane, but by cleanſing the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to become clean as the Jewes were: ſo that it is plain, this is the ſame Church, ſtanding upon the ſame foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Covenant, that that did; and therefore ſome infants are ſtill inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the priviledge of being members by the firſt grant: and if Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, then to be baptized.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That all infants were not caſt out of the Church under the Goſpel, is clear from <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. where 'tis ſaid, that ſuch <hi>branches as were broken off, were broken off for their unbeliefe.</hi> But the unbeliefe of ſome that did not beleeve, could not caſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150263:26"/>out of the Church the children of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving Jewes, therefore they remained ſtill in the Church. How plaine is this? I have driven this nail to the head, and let him ſhake this truth that can: I dare venture to let looſe this ſingle Argument to all the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in the world, and they will have ſomewhat to doe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it. The other two Arguments (with many more that might be brought) prove infants Church members, and therefore to be baptized: for if infants be <hi>Holy</hi> (as in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14.) if of the <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> (as in <hi>Mark</hi> 10.14.) then to be admitted Church-members, and ſo to be baptized. There is not one cavil to be made againſt theſe, but what is fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Baxter,</hi> in his book of <hi>Infants Church-member-ſhip,</hi> and therefore I ſhall ſay nothing to them here, having brought one Argument to an head, and one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is enough to prove one truth, if there were no more.</p>
               <p>But here you ſee how falſe it is that he ſayes, that our conſequences to prove infant-baptiſme, are no better then ſuch as he ſuggeſteth. All things are not true that ſuch men dare ſpeak, yea and print too. He that hath the impudence to print manifeſt falſehoods, touching matters of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150263:26"/>fact, upon hope of being beleeved by ſome that will not be at the pains to ſeek out the truth, will (you may ſuſpect) ſpeak and write many more falſehoods, in, and about, matters of faith. But I will away to his fourth Errour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His Fourth Error.</head>
               <head type="sub">That God now reveals his will not onely by the written word, but by Dreams and Viſions, more credited then the word.</head>
               <p>THis he dares not ſo confidently to affirme, as he doth the former. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the priſon (where I have heard he lately was in <hi>London,</hi> for his Hereſies) hath done him a little good, in making him to ſpeak warily ſometimes in weighty matters, though he thinks he may raile againſt honeſt men <hi>impunè;</hi> yet no leſſe then this doth he aſſert, page 7. in theſe words.<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If ſome doe hold this principle, Is it ſtrange and ridiculous unto you? Hath not God formerly revealed truth to his people by Dreames and Revelations? And dare you deny it now? Is God limited?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Here you ſee he affirmes that it ſhould
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150263:27"/>not be accounted a ſtrange thing to hold the above mentioned Principle, and he gives his reaſon for it: God did once ſo reveale himſelfe, and he is not limited.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe this is a Doctrine that ſuch unſteady ſpirits do labour to inſtill into the minds of the ſimple (though this man having to doe with an able Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, dares not to ſpeak out here as he would) I ſhall give you ſome account of the unſoundneſſe of the ſame, firſt anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to what he urges, and then giving my reaſons for the negative.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is God limited?</hi> (ſayes he) I anſwer, no, God is not limited, except by his owne will. But alas! the queſtion is not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God can doe it, but whether he will or no. If God hath declared his purpoſe to make uſe of ſuch wayes of revealing truth now, then we may expect it; elſe not upon any mans telling you, God can doe it. God can make another Sun in the Firmament, to help enlighten the World, when there is one ſufficient al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: he can maintaine our lives to us without food: but no body (I think) ha's any reaſon to expect he will do ſo, when food is to be had. So that this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation of his, ſavours of as much ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and is as impertinent as his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150263:27"/>former anſwers. But to the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>Whether we may expect God ſhould,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> or very much beleeve that he does, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale himſelfe now <hi>immediately</hi> to any by way of <hi>Dreames</hi> and <hi>Viſions,</hi> or the like?<note place="margin">Anſwer. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer. 1. We have no ground in the world, to look for any ſuch thing; there being no promiſe or word to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. 2. Sound Scripture Arguments will demonſtrate, that it is not to be lookt for by any, nor owned by us in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, eſpecially where the Scriptures are extant. And mine Arguments to prove this ſhall be drawne from the perfection of Scripture, and from thoſe Texts that witneſſe to the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> If a ſufficiency of Divine light and truth be given out in the Scriptures, then there is no need of Dreams and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions now, for the revealing of truth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Saints; and by conſequence ſuch things are not to be expected where the Scriptures are; for God doth not make uſe of things needleſſe and unneceſſary.</p>
               <p>But that a ſufficiency of Divine light and truth is given out in the Scriptures, is moſt cleare to one that denies not, (as the Papiſts doe) the perfection of Scripture.</p>
               <p>Therefore it follows, that there is no
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150263:28"/>need of Dreames and Viſions, and the like, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there is a ſufficiency in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, will appeare more plaine in the following Arguments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> That which hath enough in it to make Saints <hi>perfect,</hi> is fully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and ſufficient, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Scripture hath ſo. See 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17. where 'tis affirmed in ſo many words.</p>
               <p>Therefore the Scripture is compleat and ſufficient, without any additionall ſupply from <hi>Dreames</hi> and <hi>Extraordinary, immediate revelations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Except there be a ſtep above perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſure the light of Scripture is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. But I know not where theſe men would carry you: They dream (and would make you dream too) of ſtrange attainments beyond the Moone: But I hope my Reader will judge it enough to be made perfect; and perfection you ſee may be attained by Scripture light.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> If it be ſinfull and evill to be <hi>wiſe above what is written,</hi> then may not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny expect, or give heed to <hi>extraordinary Revelations</hi> by Viſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and be wiſe by them, beſide the written word.</p>
               <p>But it is ſinfull and evill <hi>to be wiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150263:28"/>what is written.</hi> See it in expreſſe termes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</p>
               <p>Therefore may not any expect, or give heed to extraordinary revelations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis we are the fools, and 'tis we are the weak and low perſons that confine our ſelves to what is written, and dare not goe an hairs-breadth beyond it: but they are the wiſe, and ſpirituall, and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated Doctours, that converſe with God immediately, and receive truth beyond the line of Scripture, as they phanſy: But this ſatisfies my ſpirit, that 'tis <hi>Pauls</hi> judgement (and not <hi>Pauls,</hi> but the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God by him) that ſuch wiſdome is wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>You may perhaps object.<note place="margin">Object.</note> Scripture-light is perfect, ſo far, as it diſcovers the mind of God; but that does not hinder but that God may reveale truth to ſome, even beyond what is held forth in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>I anſwer. 1. Scripture,<note place="margin">Anſwer. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> as hath been ſhewed, is abſolutely compleat in it ſelfe, and as to Saints too; it having enough to make them compleat and perfect, and therefore there is no need of another way to reveale more truth then what is in the Scripture. 2. As <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets were faithfull in their places: So was
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150263:29"/>Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.2. <hi>faithfull to him that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him, viz.</hi> to be the great Prophet and Teacher of his people. Now where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in lies his faithfullneſſe? why, even in laying downe a ſufficient rule and light for the Saints to be guided by; the which he did by his Apoſtles in the Scripture. Theſe men doe not conſider how much they take from the honour of Chriſt, while they dreame of additionall revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, beſide the light of Scripture. I am afraid they are too ambitious of ſharing with Chriſt in the honour of giving laws unto men: And ſo they may be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the opinion of being entruſted with the diſcovery of things not revealed in Scripture, they care not though Chriſt ſuffer as unfaithfull, in not diſcovering all that is needfull. Away with ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable pride.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Object. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Though Chriſt were faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full by himſelfe and Apoſtles to declare the whole mind of God: yet many of thoſe things that were done and ſpoken by them are not written.</p>
               <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> All that was done and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, for the ſubſtance is contained in the Scriptures, that are left by God unto his Church: which I prove.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150263:29"/>
1.<note place="margin">Reaſ. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> From thoſe Texts that ſpeak to that purpoſe. As <hi>Luke</hi> 1. begin. and <hi>Acts</hi> 1. begin. and alſo 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. begin. where <hi>John</hi> (who writ laſt of all the Apoſtles.) ſayes (ſpeaking in his owne name, and in the name of the reſt of the pen-men of Scripture) <hi>That which we have ſeen and heard, declare we unto you;</hi> that is, all that which we have ſeen and heard for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; for that indefinite Propoſition is equivalent to an univerſall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Neither could Jeſus Chriſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have been faithfull, for his faithfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe lies not in affording ſufficient light unto that age of the Church in which he lived on earth, but in providing a perfect ſtanding Rule for all the Saints unto the end of the world: he is called faithfull, not onely in reſpect of Saints living in the dayes of his fleſh, but in reſpect of all, in all ages of the world. So that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account it is clear, that as he did in the dayes of his fleſh declare ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the will of the Father unto the world by himſelfe, and his extraordinary Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; and confirmed his doctrine to be of God, by wonderfull works and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles: ſo he did leave the ſubſtance, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſumme or briefe of this Doctrine (and ſo much of the works as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150263:30"/>is requiſite to the confirmation of the ſame) upon record in Scripture for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-ages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Object.</note> You may ſay, although Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be perfect, and we grant that all truth is wrapt up in it: yet many things lying darkly there, it may pleaſe God to come in to ſome in an extraordinary way, by Viſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to reveale the truth.</p>
               <p>I anſwer.<note place="margin">Anſw. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 1. It may pleaſe God, but what reaſon ha's any man to beleeve or expect that God ſhould do ſo now, when he hath ſufficiently revealed all truth in Scripture already?</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is nothing in Scripture ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be knowne by Chriſtians, that lies ſo dark there, but that it may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by thoſe ordinary helps that God affords to his people, without any ſuch extraordinary wayes. God ha's gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out his ſpirit unto his people, to heal the blindneſſe of their minds, and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of their hearts, which is the chiefe ground of the obſcurity of Scripture to us (for Scripture is not dark in it ſelfe, but by the reaſon of the darkneſſe of mans heart, that receives not the truth thereof) And he ha's alſo given the ordinary help of Humane Learning (as knowledge of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150263:30"/>the Tongues, Antiquity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) unto men in office, for the unfolding of the darker places of Scripture. Now by theſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary helps, thoſe things that are not ſo cleare in Scripture, may be brought to light, though there be no ſuch extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary means as theſe men dream of.</p>
               <p>But in the next place, there is this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be ſaid againſt any ſuch extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way of revealing truth now.</p>
               <p>If God doth in ſuch an extraordinary way reveale truth to any now, either the end thereof is private, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, reſpecting thoſe onely to whom ſuch a diſcovery is made: Or elſe the end is more publick and generall, reſpecting others to whom ſuch (as have this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary diſcovery of truth) are to deliver over the ſame from God.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall ſhew you, God doth ſo reveale himſelfe in neither of theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, and therefore not at all.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God doth not (in ſuch an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary way) reveale truth to any, with reſpect to their private, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular edification. This appears, 1. In that he hath ordained the Scriptures for this end, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17. He hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned preaching for this end, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.28. He hath appointed Miniſters in office for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150263:31"/>this end, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11.12. In all which Scriptures you find expreſt, the meanes which God hath appointed for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and perfecting of the Saints: ſo that we cannot ſuppoſe (where any o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe means are, viz. <hi>Scriptures, Preaching faithfull Miniſters</hi>) that God ſhould edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his people by giving in Truth to them by <hi>Viſions,</hi> or ſuch like <hi>extraordinary wayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſecondly, I would faine know whether ever Scripture doth ſay, that God hath appointed <hi>extraordinary revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> by Viſion, or the like, for the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate good and edification of any Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver (as it ſayes of the meanes before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) and whether the end of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary manifeſtations of truth hath not been ever chiefly the good and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of others, to whom, ſuch as have had the revelation, were to Preach it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I would know whether that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14. <hi>[How ſhall they beleeve i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him of whom they have not heard? And how ſhall they heare without a Preacher?]</hi> Doth not confine the Production and increaſe of faith, unto the meanes before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? And if it be ſo, then queſtionleſſe God does not give <hi>extraordinary revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> with reſpect unto the edification o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch particular perſons as have the ſaid
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150263:31"/>
                  <hi>Revelations</hi> given in to them, for we find he hath appointed certaine ordinary means to work by; the which he hath a purpoſe (as far as we can find in his revealed will) to confine himſelfe unto.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I prove alſo that God doth not, in ſuch an extraordinary way, reveale him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to any now with reſpect to others whom ſuch (as have truth thus revealed) may informe of the Truth: and that upon this reaſon; Becauſe my <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>Viſion,</hi> is not ſufficient to make out truth to another; unleſſe I have <hi>miracles</hi> to prove Gods ſpeaking in and by me: But none now work <hi>miracles,</hi> therefore <hi>extraordinary revelations</hi> now, would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, and by conſequence are not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God: for God doth not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine or appoint ſuch means as are inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient as to their end.</p>
               <p>That my <hi>Revelation</hi> or <hi>Viſion,</hi> is not ſufficient to make out truth unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without <hi>miracles</hi> going with the ſame, is evident, in that, without <hi>miracles</hi> I cannot give to any man a demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the Viſion or Revelation (that I pretend to have) is of God, and if it be doubtfull, whether my Revelation be of God, 'twill be doubtfull too whither that which is pretended to be revealed,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150263:32"/>be Truth. So that you ſee I have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proved, that God does not now reveale himſelfe to any by viſions, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary revelations, either in the firſt or ſecond reſpect, and therefore not at all.</p>
               <p>It remaines then, that you muſt take this for one of <hi>Colliers</hi> Dreames, viz. <hi>That God does now reveale truth to his people, by Dreams or Viſions, and not by the Scriptures only, where they are enjoyed.</hi> Wherfore Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, be very wary of ſuch intimations, that God may ſometime in ſuch a way reveale himſelfe unto his people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They are but the Devils baits to fetch off your hearts by little and little from that ſure foundation that is laid for you by Chriſt himſelfe, in the revealed word and will of God: which if you once forſake, and give heed to the giddy Principles of theſe men, you will ſoone make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of faith, and be wrapt up in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and darkneſſe.</p>
               <p>Neither be you troubled, if they aſſault you with thoſe Scriptures which ſpeak to this purpoſe. <hi>They ſhall be all taught of God. The Annointing ſhall teach you. The day-ſtar ſhall ariſe in your hearts. The Spirit ſhall lead you into all Truth,</hi> &amp;c. For ſuch expreſſions doe onely ſignifie that ſweet
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150263:32"/>and heavenly way in which the Lord do's enlighten the minds of his people, by (not without) the ordinary means be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expreſt.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, that <hi>in God we live, move, and have our being,</hi> in reſpect of our naturall life; and yet we doe not ſo much as once think of living without food, ſleep, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the outward ſupports of life: even ſo, though it be ſaid, God teaches, and the ſpirit teaches, yet let us not dream that this is <hi>immediately,</hi> and without the uſe of <hi>meanes.</hi> I would fain know of thoſe that wait ſo much for immediate teaching, whether ever they got ſo high, as to live without the uſe of the outward meanes of relieving and ſupporting nature, upon a reliance on this truth, that God is the author and preſerver of naturall life, and that they live in him: if not, I ſhall give little credit to them, while they talk of living ſpiritually in the enjoyment, and further manifeſtation of Truth, without the uſe of the <hi>outward meanes,</hi> appointed by God for that end. As God is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of ſpirituall life, ſo is he of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life alſo. If thou be one that canſt live naturally without food, I will not much blame thee if thou ſay, thou canſt live ſpiritually, and thrive in further
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150263:33"/>diſcoveries of truth, without the help of any of the meanes before expreſt. But I ſhall ſay no more to this Queſtion, having ſaid enough (I think) to prove, that it is a groſſe Errour, to ſay, that God now reveals his will, not onely by the written word, but by <hi>Dreams</hi> and <hi>Viſions,</hi> which are to be credited equally to, or more then the word. I deſcend unto his next Errour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His Fifth Errour.</head>
               <head type="sub">That the Saints need not aske the pardon of ſinne, and that it is forme and cuſtome that carries them to this Petition, FORGIVE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R SINS.</head>
               <p>THis horrible, heterodox, unchriſtian, unſanctified Principle, he vents in his plea for the fourth Errour charged upon the Anabaptiſts. In theſe words,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>While the ſoule lives in the enjoyment of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P.G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>and love, it's then forme or cuſtome that carrieth him to that Petition: but when a ſoul apprehends the want of pardon, let him aske it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See how he labours to deceive you,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:150263:33"/>and to give you out his poyſon in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar'd words. <hi>If any one apprehends the want of pardon, let him aske it,</hi> but immediately before he ſayes, a Chriſtian while he is in a good temper, <hi>while he lives in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of mercy and love</hi> (as his words are) cannot put up that Petition, except for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally and cuſtomarily. Is not this brave Divinity?</p>
               <p>He layes down nothing to prove what he ſayes, he hopes the novelty of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and its compliance with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall pride of mans heart, will make it paſſe upon his owne word onely; but let us weigh ſomewhat of that which may be ſaid againſt this licentious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Did not Chriſt teach and command his Diſciples to pray, <hi>Forgive us our ſins,</hi> Mat. 6.12?</item>
                  <item>2. Did not they <hi>live in the enjoyment of mercy and love,</hi> when this command was given them? Were they not ſuch then as could call God Father? And I hope ſuch may goe for men <hi>living in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of mercy and love,</hi> as by the ſpirit of Adoption can come unto God as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and owne him in ſo neer a relation. Now it is plaine, touching the Diſciples, that then, when they had a diſcovery of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150263:34"/>the neareſt and ſweeteſt relation unto God, and could come to him, ſaying, <hi>Our Father.</hi> I ſay, even then were they bid to pray, <hi>Forgive us our ſins.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Though I ſhould grant that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles had not ſuch a full enjoyment of mercy and love, as this man pretends to (for obſerve it, nothing will ſatisfie this kind of men, unleſſe they may be thought (in ſome thing or other) to be more excellent then Apoſtles themſelves, and ſuch extraordinary inſtruments as Chriſt entruſted in laying the foundation of the Goſpel-Church.) I ſay, though I ſhould be ſo far indulgent to their pride and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogance, as to grant this: yet would Chriſt teach any of his people to pray for ſuch a thing, as no Chriſtian living in the enjoyment of mercy and love (which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very true Chriſtian ought to doe) can pray for, but either out of forme or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome? that were ſtrange.</item>
               </list>
               <p>If ſuch as <hi>live in the enjoyment of mercy and love</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch as have a diſcovery o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods mercy and love to their ſouls) may not pray, <hi>For give us our ſins,</hi> then ſee how neceſſarily ſome, or all of theſe abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties will follow from <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Either Chriſts command there <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not to be obeyed, which (as far <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:150263:34"/>judge) is his opinion. Or,</item>
                  <item>2. The Diſciples had not the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Gods mercy, and love to their ſouls: and if ſo, then,</item>
                  <item>3. A man may be able to owne, and come to God as a Father (as they did) and yet not know Gods mercy and love to his ſoul; which is a contradiction.</item>
                  <item>4. 'Twill follow, that Chriſt teaches and commands his Saints to doe ſuch things, as (if they be rightly informed) cannot be done, but formally and out of cuſtome: and are not theſe groſſe abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, ſuch as a pious Chriſtian cannot beare?</item>
               </list>
               <p>But Beleevers are juſtified from ſin,<note place="margin">Object.</note> and ſo may not pray for the pardoning of ſin, becauſe it is already done in their Juſtification.</p>
               <p>If this be good arguing,<note place="margin">Anſw. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> how can we juſtifie Chriſts command bidding his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to pray for forgiveneſſe of ſin? Were not they juſtified perſons? I hope none will deny it. But to clear this.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt diſtinguiſh of two acts of Grace in the juſtifying of ſinners, <hi>Viz.</hi> To juſtifie a ſinner from all his ſins that he ſtands <hi>actually</hi> guilty of; and then a continuation of juſtification from ſin, as it is afterward daily committed. For it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150263:35"/>is one thing to pardon, another thing to continue to pardon: now this latter, Chriſtians <hi>(living in the enjoyment of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and love)</hi> may, and muſt pray for.</p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Reaſ. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Becauſe all the ſure mercies of the Covenant, are to be received in a way of prayer. See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.37. where obſerve, that notwithſtanding the Lord declares his purpoſe <hi>to take away their iniquities,</hi> verſ. 33. and to give out to them other mercies of the Covenant, yet he laies in this caution, <hi>verſ.</hi> 37. <hi>Notwithſtanding I will be ſought unto, or enquired of to doe this for them.</hi> He will have pardon ſued out by Prayer, in order to the particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it, in reſpect of particular fins daily committed.</p>
               <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Reaſ. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Chriſt he continually intercedes and prayes for Beleevers in Heaven, and that for this particular favour, viz. <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin.</hi> See 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>My little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, theſe things write I unto you, that ye ſin not. And if any man ſin, we have an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous,</hi> &amp;c. Mark it, if Saints <hi>ſin,</hi> they have Chriſt for an <hi>Advocate,</hi> now wherefore ſhould he Advocate or plead for them, upon their ſinning, if not for pardon? Now doth Chriſt plead for the pardon of beleevers, and may not they for their own pardon?
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150263:35"/>is not Chriſts interceſſion in Heaven, a good rule for our Prayers on Earth? You have another place to this purpoſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. From which Scripture I doe demand why Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>able to ſave to the utmoſt, in that he ever intercedes,</hi> unleſſe it be becauſe by his interceſſion he obtaines a continuation of pardon, and an application of it in reſpect of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſins dayly committed. And ſhall any one think that there is need Chriſt ſhould pray in Heaven for pardon of ſin, and no need beleevers ſhould on Earth? Ah! 'Tis a brave Religion you ſhall learne of theſe Doctors, if you have a minde to credit them. But it matters not what it be ſo it be new, and contrary to the teaching of the faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt, whom this Pamphleter labours to vilifie.</p>
               <p>I could bring you forth the examples of many of the moſt eminentand pretious Saints in Scripture, that have ſought pardon of ſin, yea and that with bleeding, broken hearts, were it not that hee'l be ready to ſay, theſe men <hi>lived not in the enjoyment of mercy and love,</hi> as now we do. But I ſhall rather think in very deed, that he lives yet in the boſome of Hell, and wrath, then queſtion their living in the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150263:36"/>enjoyment of mercy and love, who in Scripture are brought in ſuing for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin, ſuch as were <hi>Moſes, David,</hi> and the Prophets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some other abſurdities are ſcattered throughout page 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. in his defence of the <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>As 1. Where he affirmes, that <hi>the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle condemnes-going to law as a ſin,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. when as the words make it plaine, that he condemnes onely their going to Law, <hi>before the unjuſt and infidels.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Where he blames his Adverſary as contradicting himſelfe, in ſaying, <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts hold that wars are uſeleſſe,</hi> and again afterward, that <hi>they are tumultuous,</hi> &amp;c. when as the contradiction is in their Principles, who can Preach downe the lawfulneſſe of going to war at one time, and yet move wars and tumuls to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their deſigne, at another time. I wiſh thoſe that are in Authority would look well to them, I hope they doe.</item>
                  <item>3. Where he urges a <hi>generall tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> becauſe <hi>Magiſtrates by their Civill Power cannot Convert;</hi> as if there were no uſe of the Magiſtrates Power in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining mens impiety, and compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to conformity in ſubmitting to converting Ordinances, unleſſe they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150263:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>could alſo change the heart.</item>
                  <item>4. Where he denies the diſtinction of three perſons in the God-head, becauſe the word Perſon is not uſed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Though <hi>John</hi> ſayes, <hi>There are Three, the Father, the Word, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and theſe three are one;</hi> Of which words there can be no ſence, unleſſe they be <hi>Three Perſons</hi> (as the Church of Chriſt underſtands the word Perſon) for if they be <hi>Three,</hi> what three? if not <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe, and many ſuch like abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, with his railings intermixt, I ſhall paſſe over, not doubting but the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will rank them among the reſt of his Errours, which I have, and ſhall ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently confute.</p>
               <p>The next Errour is the maine and principall ſcope of his Booke: and 'tis as followes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:150263:37"/>
               <head>His Sixth Error.</head>
               <head type="sub">That Gifted Brethren may exerciſe the Miniſteriall or Paſtorall act of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a conſtituted Church, without a Call to the Office of a Miniſter.</head>
               <p>THis Poſition comes neareſt to what I can poſſibly gather (by reading o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Diſcourſe) to be his meaning in what he writes in Anſwer to a Treatiſe Intituled, <hi>The Pulpit Guarded,</hi> &amp;c. Though I confeſſe, in laying downe this he ſpeaks moſt notable contradictions, as I ſhall ſhew you by and by; ſo that a man can hardly know what he would have in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſadneſſe.</p>
               <p>And here (Reader) know.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That my purpoſe is not to handle the twenty Arguments that he pretends to Anſwer, and to make a particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; for ſo I ſhould weary thee out too much with the diſcovery of his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and abſurdneſſe, which I can ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently rip open, going a ſhorter way to work.</item>
                  <item>2. This lies upon M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Hall</hi> his Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt, who is able I doubt not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150263:37"/>his owne Arguments if he lift.</item>
                  <item>3. It may be all M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Halls</hi> Arguments in this controverſie may not be my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments. But this I'le ſay, for my part I finde nothing ſaid againſt any of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Hals</hi> Arguments, that can be taken for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation by any that can ſee where the ſtrength of an Argument doth lye: ſo that it is like he may never reply, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending his Arguments untouched, though ſuppoſed by the <hi>Collier</hi> to be <hi>Routed.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>But though I will not (upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) make a particular reply (which would be too tedious) yet I ſhall give thee ſome few obſervations upon the whole in generall: which will help thee to ſee (if thou haſt but halfe an eye) the invalidity and weakneſſe of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: and then annex my additionall Reaſons againſt him.</p>
               <p>Verily, if the man had ever had the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of being judicious, able, and ſolid, an underſtanding Reader would think him here to be out of his wits. That you may ſee this as well as I, I ſhall lay down ſome Obſervations, which may ſerve you inſtead of a key to let you in to every particular anſwer of his, to ſee the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ignorance, and impertinency of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:150263:38"/>
                  <hi>Obſer.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Obſer. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> You may take notice, that he does moſt pittifully ſay, I Sir, No Sir (and that in divers particulars) in his Diſcourſe, upon the Queſtion now in debate. I ſhall give you a taſt in the inſtances following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. One where he tells you, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians may Preach as gifted Brethren, without any other call but their gifts; yet they may not intrude into the office of a Miniſter. <hi>To uſurp the Miniſteriall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>is ſinne,</hi> page 17. and yet he ſayes, page 29. <hi>There is no one thing that belongs to a Paſtour, or Miniſter, but a gifted Brother may doe it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. He ſayes (as before) <hi>'Tis ſinfull to uſurp the miniſteriall office:</hi> And yet he ſaye, page 45. <hi>That the duty or work of a Miniſter is not ſo diſtinct, but that another may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. In page 45. He ſayes, <hi>A Paſtour or Miniſter in Office, is in a diſtinct manner to attend upon the duties of teaching,</hi> &amp;c. ſo as gifted Brethren are not to doe; but how? Not altogether, for in the ſame page he ſayes, <hi>Yet not ſo but that they may uſe another Calling;</hi> and if ſo, 'tis but ſometimes onely that they can attend upon teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and other miniſteriall duties. And you ſhall hear him ſay, page 29. <hi>That
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150263:38"/>gifted Brethren may, and muſt doe theſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as often as time, opportunity, and liberty calls for it:</hi> That is, as often as they are able, and have a mind to it: O brave Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomachie!</item>
                  <item>4. Sometimes he ſayes expreſly, <hi>The Saints are all Prophets,</hi> as page 60. where he not onely ſayes it, but proves it, after his manner of proving, by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Every ſpirituall man is a Prophet, the Saints are all ſpirituall men, therefore all Prophets.</hi> And yet againe (when he is driven to it by a plaine Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.29.) he ſayes, <hi>All are not Prophets,</hi> as in page 21.</item>
                  <item>5 He ſayes, <hi>All have not the gift to ſpeak to the edifying of the Church,</hi> ſo page 21. and yet page 83. he ſayes, <hi>He ſhould looke upon that member as uſeleſſe, that hath not ſome gift or other for good in the Church.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. He ſayes, Gifted Brethren ought to Preach, it is their <hi>Duty</hi> to Preach; and that in ſuch a Publique and authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive way, as Miniſters are by their office, to doe (for he admits not of any diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction betweene private and publique Preaching) and yet he ſayes, page 84. <hi>By office ſuch are not Preachers.</hi> A fine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction! a Preacher by <hi>duty,</hi> but not by <hi>office.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:150263:39"/>
7. He demands in great fury, page 87. where ever we read <hi>Prophets</hi> called <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours,</hi> or Paſtours and Teachers called Prophets; and ſayes, 'tis Logick learnt from the Devil, to ſpeak ſo: and yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and anon in his diſcourſe, he ſayes. <hi>Prophets are Teachers,</hi> and proves that gifted Brethren are Teachers, becauſe Prophets.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Sure, the man is in good hope, that the moſt of his Readers will be men of bad memories, or judgements, or both; that when they are reading one page, will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get what he ſays in another: or he would not venture thus to contradict himſelfe. But he holds a Wolfe by the ears (as the Proverbe is) and pitifully puzled you may ſee he is. One part or other of the contradiction he knows is true, but which he cannot tell; and therefore he will be ſure to ſpeak both, that he may be ſomtimes found in the truth. Surely either this man hath but a bad cauſe to plead, or elſe the cauſe hath falne upon a bad Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate in him to plead for it, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he talks of gifts ſo much. He need not have another to anſwer him, while he is ſo good at confuting himſelf. Much of my deſigne is to help the weaker ſort to ſee this, that is very open to ſuch as are intelligent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:150263:39"/>
                  <hi>Obſer.</hi> 2. You may obſerve further,<note place="margin">Obſer. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> that he never diſtinguiſheth of <hi>Preaching,</hi> nor doth he define what <hi>Preaching</hi> is, that yee might underſtand what he meanes, when he pleads for the lawfulneſſe of gifted Brethrens Preaching. But his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne is to cheat you if he can, with am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous termes, never adding any expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them.</p>
               <p>All the diſtinction that he makes of <hi>Teachers,</hi> is onely this; <hi>Teachers</hi> by <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> and Teachers by <hi>gift, without Office.</hi> As good as if he had ſaid, <hi>Teachers</hi> that are ſo indeed, and <hi>Teachers</hi> that are not ſo, but onely eſteem themſelves ſo; or at beſt might be ſo, if the <hi>power</hi> of the Church did call them into the <hi>office.</hi> As if one ſhould ſay, a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> by gift, and a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> by office. He confiders not, that, as the <hi>gift</hi> diſpoſeth a man to the <hi>office,</hi> ſo only the <hi>office</hi> diſpoſeth him unto the execution of the <hi>gift.</hi> A man <hi>gifted</hi> for a Magiſtrate, is no Magiſtrate, nor may execute the work of a Magiſtrate, till called to the <hi>office;</hi> even ſo a man <hi>gifted</hi> to be a Teacher, is no Teacher, nor may execute the work of a Teacher, till he be called to that office: except in the caſes ſignified in ſtating the controverſie.</p>
               <p>All the definition he gives of <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:150263:40"/>(that you may know what it is) is page 59. where he ſayes, <hi>Preaching is but a ſpeech, or ſpeaking of words:</hi> and if ſo (for all his pretended gifts) a Parrat may preach as well as he. But 'tis well he ſayeth, <hi>Preaching is a ſpeaking of words;</hi> for many of thoſe that undertake publique Preaching without any miſſion, <hi>ſpeake words</hi> ('tis true) but many times no ſence: let their judicious hearers (if there be any) be judges.</p>
               <p>But he meanes (I ſuppoſe) ſpeaking words unto ſpirituall edification, and if this be all the Preaching he pleads for, to be allowed to gifted Brethren, why doth he contend? when as brotherly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, exhortation, inſtruction, reproof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are granted by his Adverſary, not to gifted Brethren onely, but to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in their proper ſphere, and keeping within their line. I ſay this is granted to all Chriſtians (even to women alſo) who yet I hope may not be Preachers.</p>
               <p>I think no honeſt heart (even among them that oppoſe his opinion) doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to abridge Chriſtians liberty in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the edification one of another, in ſuch a way, nay rather we ſtir them up, and provoke them (to the uſe of their liberty, do I ſay, nay) to the practiſe of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150263:40"/>their duty herein. But can any one be ſo blind as not to ſee a vaſt difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>publique, paſtorall duties</hi> of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter (which he is obliged to by his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, called in the Scripture, <hi>feeding the flock of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.) And thoſe <hi>Chriſtian duties</hi> that lye upon all Beleevers, enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſuch language as this, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer thy brother to ſin, but ſhalt reprove him and tell him his fault,</hi> Lev. 19.17. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ane another with theſe words,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.18. And againe, <hi>They ſhall ſpeake of thy Kingdome, and talke of thy power,</hi> Pſal. 145.11. And 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4. <hi>That we may be able to comfort them which are in trouble, by the comfort wherewith we our ſelves are comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God.</hi> (Places which among others he urges for publique Preaching of men not in office.) I ſay is any man ſo blind as not to ſee a difference betweene theſe? Is it not plaine that though they may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in <hi>matter,</hi> yet doe differ in <hi>forme,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Forma dat nomen, &amp; eſſe.</note> which is that which gives name and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to things.</p>
               <p>But this he would not have you take notice of, if you doe, a great part of his Book is anſwered without much a doe. Wherefore he denies any difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>publique</hi> and <hi>private</hi> Preaching. He ſayes, <hi>This diſtinction came from Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P.G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150263:41"/>ha's no footing in Scripture, if in private, why not in publike? if we may preach to one or two in private, why not to a thouſand in publike?</hi> page 88. 91.<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Much of the controverſie depends on the clearing of this, and If I can prove this diſtinction from Scripture, and ſhew you that there is a ſpecificall difference betweene <hi>publique</hi> and <hi>private preaching:</hi> Preaching taken in a <hi>large,</hi> and Preaching taken in a <hi>ſtrict</hi> ſence, then you'l ſay that the heart-ſtrings of many of his anſwers and arguments are cut, and that nothing is remaining, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident expreſſions, to give any life to them.</p>
               <p>This I ſhall doe (God willing) by two Arguments, grounded, not on Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teſtimony onely, but alſo on his owne conceſſions: Thus,<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>If we find in Scripture that all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians may <hi>Preach,</hi> take Preaching in a <hi>large</hi> ſence, for the <hi>private duties</hi> that they owe one to another: and that they may not all <hi>Preach,</hi> take preaching in a <hi>ſtrict</hi> ſence, for <hi>publique paſtorall preaching,</hi> then there is a ſpecificall difference between theſe: for otherwiſe the ſame thing would be to the ſame perſons lawfull and unlawfull; which is a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:150263:41"/>
But I prove by Scripture. 1. That all Chriſtians may <hi>Preach,</hi> take Preaching in a <hi>large ſence,</hi> for brotherly exhortation, admonition, reproof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4. with many other places; concerning which Scriptures, you may obſerve, that they ſpeak not to ſome <hi>Gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Brethren</hi> onely, but to all the godly indefinitely. Beſides, he himſelfe grants this ever and anon in his Diſcourſe. 2. I prove that all Chriſtians may not <hi>preach,</hi> take Preaching in a <hi>ſtrict ſence</hi> (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) by the plaine words of the Apoſtle in 1 Cor. 12.29. <hi>Are all Teachers?</hi> which Queſtion he himſelfe acknowledges, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports a deniall, and is as much as <hi>All chriſtians are not teachers;</hi> and ſo may not take upon them to teach, that is in a ſtrict proper ſence.</p>
               <p>So that the inference is moſt undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that there is a ſpecificall difference betweene the one way of Teaching or Preaching, and the other. Unleſſe you will beleeve the Scripture ſpeaks contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions (as he does) making, as I ſaid before, the ſame thing lawfull and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull to the ſame perſons.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, I argue thus.<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>If it be lawfull for <hi>Women</hi> to Preach
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150263:42"/>
                  <hi>privately,</hi> take Preaching in a large ſence, and forbidden them to Preach <hi>publiquely</hi> and in the Church, then there is a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall difference betweene theſe, and a good ground in Scripture for the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>publique</hi> and <hi>private</hi> Preaching.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Women</hi> may Preach <hi>privately,</hi> take Preaching in the large ſence. See 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. compared with 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Acts</hi> 18.26. <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.1. &amp;c. And 'tis forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them to Preach <hi>publiquely,</hi> even in the Church. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34, 35. ☞ 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11, 12. Therefore this diſtinction is grounded on Scripture, and publique and private Preaching doe ſpecifically differ one from the other. And yet hath not this fellow boldneſſe enough to puffe away ſolid Arguments meerly with ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>there is no ſuch diſtinction found in Scripture,</hi> and that <hi>'tis fetcht from Rome?</hi> Ah alas! if any thing galls them, it comes preſently from <hi>Rome,</hi> 'tis <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> you may be affrighted with ſuch bug-bears, without reaſon if you liſt.</p>
               <p>My chriſtian friends (you whoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment I aim at in this Diſcourſe, that your fellowſhip with the Father of Lights may be more conſtant and ſweet) take this Leſſon away with you. The beſt Engine <hi>myſticall Antichriſt</hi> ha's to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150263:42"/>his deſigne among Chriſtians, is to be all againſt <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> in appearance. He is ſure to have beſt ſucceſſe among well meaning people, when he is in the forme and appearance of an Angel of light.</p>
               <p>But to returne to mine Adverſary (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne doe I ſay? I think I never went from him in ſpeaking of <hi>myſticall Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Hee'l ſay, the Apoſtle ſayes, 1 Cor. 12.29.<note place="margin">Object.</note> 
                  <hi>All are not Teachers,</hi> becauſe all are not gifted: but all that are gifted, are Teachers, and may Preach.</p>
               <p>This anſwers to neither my firſt,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> nor ſecond Argument to prove the diſtinction of Preaching above mentioned.</p>
               <p>It anſwers not my firſt; for, 1. All Chriſtians are gifted according to the meaſure they have received: yea, and he himſelfe ſayes,<note place="margin">Gradus non variant ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem.</note> that every member ha's his gift whereby to be uſefull to the Church, page 83. Though ſome in one degree, ſome in another. (which is no prejudice to the thing in hand) 2. If he ſhould deny it, as indeed elſewhere he does (for he can ſpeak contradictions) yet the Scriptures before mentioned in proof of the firſt branch of the ſecond Propoſition of my firſt Argument doe prove the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> That all Chriſtians
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150263:43"/>may and ought to teach by brotherly admonition, advice, reproof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore are gifted (according to their meaſure) thereunto. And if ſo, then <hi>Paul</hi> does not ſay, <hi>All are not teachers,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all are not gifted, for all are gifted according to their degree, and ſo are Teachers and Preachers; take Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for private Preaching, and in the large ſence before mentioned. But his meaning muſt needs be, <hi>All are not teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> that is, <hi>Miniſteriall, Paſtorall, publique</hi> Teachers. And ſo it affords us a ground for a diſtinction of two kinds of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or Teaching, ſpecifically differenced, as we affirme.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Much leſſe doth it weaken my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Argument. For are <hi>Women</hi> forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to <hi>teach in publique,</hi> in the Church, becauſe they are not gifted? 'Tis known many Women are gifted to ſpeak to the edification of others, and may uſe ſuch gifts as they have in a <hi>private</hi> way, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully (as was proved even now) but not <hi>publiquely,</hi> and in the Church: which layes a good foundation for the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ſhewes (though he thinks it ſo ſtrange, page 91.) That it may be lawfull <hi>to teach privately before a few,</hi> by brotherly exhortation, advice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150263:43"/>
                  <hi>not to teach publiquely before a thouſand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Carry this alſo along with you as you read his anſwers (if you think you may waſt ſo much time as to read them) and tell me whether moſt of them are not turned into meer Scelitons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſer.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Obſer. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> You ſhall (moreover) find he ſeldome takes any notice of the thing that is in Queſtion, or (as a ſound hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of controverſies) at all diſtinguiſheth <hi>controverſa, a non controverſis,</hi> things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted from things not in diſpute; but in many of his anſwers <hi>beats the air,</hi> and not his Adverſary: and therefore no wonder he dreamt of <hi>Routing</hi> the <hi>Pulpit Guard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Whereas the Queſtion (as ſtated by his Antagoniſt) is, whether any may Preach <hi>in a conſtituted Church,</hi> unleſſe they be called unto the office of a Miniſter. Thoſe Scriptures, or the moſt of them, that he grounds many of his anſwers on, ſpeak onely of Preaching to Infidells, and <hi>in a Church not conſtituted.</hi> As <hi>Acts</hi> 8.1.4. Touching the Preaching of the <hi>ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Brethren,</hi> Acts 9.20. concerning <hi>Sauls</hi> Preaching, as he pretends, before called to be a Miniſter: with ſome other Scriptures, which he quotes over and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver againe: 'Tis evident they come not
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150263:44"/>up to the Queſtion in hand, which is, whether ſuch as are not Miniſters in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, may Preach <hi>in a Church conſtituted.</hi> But more of this when I come to anſwer to the ſeverall Scriptures he grounds all his Diſcourſe upon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas the Queſtion ſtated is of <hi>Preaching</hi> taken in a <hi>ſtrinct ſence;</hi> for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall, Miniſteriall, Publique Preaching, Preaching Authoritatively: he diſputed for Preaching in a <hi>large ſence,</hi> as it figni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies any declaration of truth for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of ſouls, which no body ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to belong to the duty of (not gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Brethren onely as he ſpeaks, but) all Chriſtians indifferently in their ſtations and capacities. Yea, and can you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it? This valiant <hi>Router</hi> doth ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times take up his heels and run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and in a manner grant all in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, viz. <hi>That no gifted brother may preach as one in office;</hi> that 'tis <hi>ſin to uſurp the Miniſteriall office:</hi> and yet thinks he is conquering all the while.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whereas the Queſtion is, whether men not in office may Preach in the ſence before expreſt, except in extraordinary caſes: all that he proves, is, that ſuch did Preach in <hi>extraordinary caſes,</hi> which is not diſputed. And he would faine
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150263:44"/>make men beleeve, that that which may be done in <hi>Extraordinary</hi> caſes, may be done in <hi>Ordinary,</hi> as page 72. As though rules of order, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not (by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment) to give place ſometimes to more weighty and <hi>morally</hi> neceſſary things. I would fain know of him (who I perceive is an <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi>) whether he, having gained a Proſelyte, if he ſhould fall ſick before he were dipt, would not deferre the dipping of him untill he were well? Though the rule be to Baptize ſtreight way upon beleeving. I know theſe men uſe to be quick enough with Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites made by them, and will be ſure to dip them (if they can) while they are in a good mood; and yet I think they would defer Baptiſme upon dangerous ſickneſſe, an extraordinary caſe. Beſides, pray read <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.3, 4. Does not Chriſt there defend <hi>David</hi> in doing that in an <hi>extraordinary caſe,</hi> which the Text ſayes, <hi>was otherwiſe unlawfull for him to doe?</hi> Yea, you find verſ. 7. Chriſt layes down the generall ſtanding rule by which we are to walk in ſuch caſes, ſaying, <hi>I will have mercy and not ſacrifice.</hi> And yet this man thinks it ſtrange that we ſhould grant it lawfull, that ſuch as are really gifted to teach, ſhould teach publiquely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150263:45"/>an externall Call, in times of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, when there are none in office to be found, and Ordination cannot well be had: and yet ſay 'tis unlawfull when no ſuch extraordinary reaſon is. Why, tell him (friendly Reader) when thou meeteſt with him (for he uſes to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der abroad) that in ſuch extraordinary caſes, <hi>God will have mercy and not ſacrifice.</hi> Thoſe tender bowels of mercy that we owe to poor ſouls, lying in darkneſſe, that cannot otherwiſe be inſtructed, may command this particular rule of <hi>Order</hi> to give place then; though when this neceſſity is over, he muſt know <hi>God will have mercy and ſacrifice too.</hi> But you may ſee the depth of this mans judgement in the matters of God.</p>
               <p>I muſt tell you Chriſtians (and I think you'l find it to be a true Rule, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heed it) <hi>One Scripture witneſſing that God hath appointed, and fixed ſome in office for the worke of the Miniſtry, to attend upon it</hi> (a thing that <hi>Collier</hi> himſelfe grants) <hi>is of more ſtrength to condemne the unlimited liberty of Preaching that he pleads for, then twenty examples of gifted mens preaching</hi> (in thoſe extraordinary times of perſecution and ſcattering of Chriſtians, which the hiſtoricall part of Scripture relates) <hi>are to defend the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:150263:45"/>
Wherefore thoſe Scriptures that ſpeak of gifted Brethrens Preaching, or tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling abroad the tidings of Jeſus Chriſt, in thoſe extraordinary unſetled times, (unſetled through the ſcattering of the Brethren) make nothing to the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For the thing diſputed, is, whether in ordinary caſes, when all things are in a calme, and quiet condition, no great ſcarcity of able honeſt men in office; and Ordination to the office may be had, whether then men not in the miniſteriall office, may practiſe publique Preaching without breach of the rule given to the Churches of Chriſt. This, which is the maine of the Queſtion, he ſayes little too, and what he does ſay, I will anſer anon.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whereas the Queſtion is, whether ſuch may preach in the ſence before ſet downe, without office, or relation and reſpect thereunto: He argues (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in his Diſcourſe) that they may preach, <hi>in order to the triall of their gifts;</hi> or elſe none can ever be duely ordained, and appointed unto the office, ſeing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation and tryall of gifts muſt go before Ordination to the office; a thing never queſtioned, but knowne to be approved of by thoſe that oppoſe his corrupt opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150263:46"/>notwithſtanding, provided it be by conſent of Paſtour and People, that ſuch Preach as are not actually inveſted with the office. We all grant, that one really gifted, may Preach, <hi>in ordine ad munus,</hi> in order to the office, or as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hall</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>per modum probationis,</hi> as Probationers.</p>
               <p>And here I ſhall remove an Objection that poſſibly might be made againſt mine owne practiſe.</p>
               <p>I acknowledge I Preacht now and then, for the ſpace of a yeare or two, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was formally ordained. But,
<list>
                     <item>1. I did ſo in order to the taking up of the Office of a Miniſter.</item>
                     <item>2. I was never againſt Ordination, and this was knowne, though ſuſpected by ſome, that were leaſt acquainted with my judgement.</item>
                     <item>3. 'Twas onely while I wanted op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of Ordination, in times of the war, and when in Baniſhment from mine owne Countrey, and before ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after my returne.</item>
                     <item>4. I did not this without the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of ſeverall able godly Miniſters, which was virtually an Ordination; and therefore this makes nothing to the countenancing of their practiſe, that ſet upon this work without reſpect to any of theſe particulars.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:150263:46"/>
Now then, if you take along with you this third Obſervation upon his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, you'l ſee that for the moſt part he meddles little with the Queſtion, but ſtrikes at randome at a man of ſtraw, of his owne ſetting up, meerly beating the air, and therefore nothing but air and vanity in his anſwers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſer.</hi> 4. You may take notice alſo,<note place="margin">Obſer. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> that while he pleads for a generall liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Preaching, even in conſtituted Churches, he does not informe you how far he would extend this, whither he meane gifted Brethren may Preach in a conſtituted Church <hi>by the conſent of the Paſtour</hi> and people: or whether he mean they may Preach <hi>whether they be willing or no:</hi> not a word of this, for his deſigne is to advance a diſorderly confuſed pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, in generall termes, which he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to owne in plain termes, diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laid downe: if it were not ſo, he could never have omitted the ſatisfying of his Reader in this.</p>
               <p>If ſo be one that pretends gifts may Preach in a Church conſtituted, <hi>without the conſent of the Paſtour,</hi> and people; then what liberty or power is left unto the Churches of Chriſt? let any man judge. If a ſtranger may come and ſuſpend a
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150263:47"/>
                  <hi>Church-officer</hi> from the execution of his Miniſteriall duties among his peopie, <hi>without his conſent,</hi> and undertake to teach them, without his approbation; where is Church-liberty and Church-power then? How are Miniſters <hi>Shephe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rds,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to keepe off Wolves from the Flock, if by the Rules of Chriſt, any Wolfe may come in under the name of a <hi>gifted Brother,</hi> and devour the flock, <hi>cum privilegio,</hi> without controule?</p>
               <p>If he intends onely that a gifted bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may teach in a conſtituted Church, by the free and unanimous conſent, and deſire of Paſtour and people, why doth he contend? This would not be denied, but that if there be one of knowne gifts, ſound in the faith, that defires to ſpeak to the edification of the people, if he have the free conſent of the Paſtour, and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he may: But alas! this will no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſerve his turne. I ſuppoſe the practiſe h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pleads for, is the ſame with that which he, and his Aſſociates have taken up, o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> comming tumultuouſly and forceably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Congregations, without conſent, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Miniſter or People, to the grea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcandall of the Goſpel. Let the tumul<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that have been made by this means in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet</hi> and <hi>Devon</hi> (what ever ha's been
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150263:47"/>done in other places) be witneſſes, that this is their practice, and therefore tis like tis that which hee here intends: and if ſo, then pray judge whether this be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Goſpel, or conſiſtent with chriſtian liberty: and whether any one of all the Scripturs hee produces in his book, doe give the leaſt countenance to the ſame; if not, then all he ſayes is vain and impertinent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">Obſer. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> In moſt of his anſwers he doth not reply to the Scripture-reaſon alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt him, but, declining that as a little too hard for him, hee anſwers by affirming the thing diſputed, and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, from ſome few Scriptures which he quotes at leaſt (I think) ten times over. So that hee anſwers by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting, and takes not off his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Arguments, but gives you in his owne. This I could ſhew you in ſeverall particulars, but that I had rather make you ſee how bad his cauſe is, then how abfurdly he manages it. Now ſith he grounds all on a few Scriptures (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by him) if I can demonſtrate the impertinency of them to his purpoſe, and clear them from ſpeaking any thing for his opinion, then you'l ſay, <hi>The Router is Routed.</hi> This I ſhall do in the next place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:150263:48"/>
               <head>Severall Scriptures opened and cleared from giving any countenance to that Babell and confuſion pleaded for, by the <hi>P. G. Routed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe two firſt Scriptures that I ſhall ſpeak to, are, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.20. The firſt ſpeaks of the <hi>ſcattered Brethren,</hi> that Preached. The ſecond of <hi>Sauls</hi> Preaching (as he ſuppoſes) before cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be a Miniſter. Theſe are brought in by him as a running verſe in the end of ſeverall anſwers, as being of great weight to his cauſe, but how little they make for him, ſhall, I hope, appear.</p>
               <p>Before I ſpeak particularly to them, let me lay you downe theſe two profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Rules</hi> as preparatory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reg.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Rule <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> In weighty things of God, a Chriſtian muſt have a certaine, evident rule to warrant his practiſe, and may not ground it upon likelihood and probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Though Scriptures be produced that make the thing ſomewhat likely, yet if they doe not neceſſarily conclude the matter in Queſtion, they are not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to lead any forth unto the practiſe of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:150263:48"/>
                  <hi>Reg.</hi> 2. Arguments drawne from Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies,<note place="margin">Rule <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> or examples of men in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are of credit, according to the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of the perſons whoſe teſtimonies, or examples they are. So that if the perſons from whoſe teſtimony or example the Argument is drawne, be fallible, in their teſtimony, or example; the Argument drawne there-from, muſt needs be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, and fallible too.</p>
               <p>Theſe two things being premiſed, I ſhal to the clearing of the two Scriptures, which preſent us with the example of the <hi>ſcattered brethren,</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> their Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>If we ſhould ſuppoſe that theſe preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents did ſuit the matter in Queſtion (as they do not) for their Preaching was not in a Church conſtituted, but to Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels. Yet,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are the examples of men not infallibly guided in what they did. This is moſt certaine as to the ſcattered bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: no man I think will ſay we have very much reaſon to judge that they were infallibly guided in what they did, and as to <hi>Saul,</hi> it is as evident too, ſuppoſing that which he affirmes, that <hi>Saul</hi> was a private Chriſtian, and not called forth to be a Miniſter, if ſo, then his example is
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150263:49"/>no more infallible then theirs. Now if there be not an infallibility in theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, they doe not neceſſarily conclude the <hi>Jus</hi> or right of the thing done, though they make it likely; which is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for Chriſtians, that (in ſuch weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty matters eſpecially) muſt walk by a certaine rule; ſo that, if I ſhould ſay no more, what is become of theſe two ſtrong holds that he flies to ſo often? At moſt they doe but conclude a likelihood of the lawfullneſſe of this practiſe which he pleads for. It concludes onely a <hi>may be,</hi> and may any go upon <hi>may bees</hi> in ſuch weighty matters?</p>
               <p>But 2. As for the <hi>ſcattered brethren,</hi> it is a great Queſtion whether the Apoſtles (that were at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> at the time of the ſcattering of the Chriſtians there) did not give them Commiſſion to Preach, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hall</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> And what ha's <hi>The P. G. Routed,</hi> to ſay to this? Why, ſayes he, <hi>The Scripture doth not ſpeake of any ſuch thing.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Very good, neither doth Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeak the contrary, and what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows then, but that it is doubtfull whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were ſent by the Apoſtles, or no: and if ſo, then ſtill doubtfull (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that example) whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man elſe may preach without an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall call.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:150263:49"/>
Beſides 3. was their preaching in a conſtituted Church, and not among the unbelieving Jewes rather? as Acts 11.19.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Was it not in an extraordinary ſeaſon? which as ha's been proved before, quite alters the caſe. This Scripture then you ſee proves nothing certaine and to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p>As for the latter Scripture concerning <hi>Saul</hi> his Preaching (before he was called to be a Miniſter, as he affirmes) 'Tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent he Preached, but that he Preached before he was called to be a Miniſter, is moſt falſe. 'Tis true, he Preached before he was ſolemnly ſet a part to be an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Gentiles; as <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2, 3. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 9.20. proves: but he was called to be a Miniſter before. And I wonder this man was not afraid to bring in <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2, 3. leaſt any ſhould have lookt into the verſe immediatly preceding, <hi>verſe</hi> 1. where it is ſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that before this he was one of the Prophets and Teachers that were at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it may be objected,<note place="margin">Object.</note> that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons there mentioned were Teachers <hi>by gift,</hi> not <hi>by office,</hi> and ſo <hi>Saul</hi> was not in office before this time.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> All the members of the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150263:50"/>Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> were Teachers by gift, according to the meaſure that they had received (for all Saints are Prophets and Teachers in that ſence, as he himſelfe ſayes) but theſe were Prophets and Teachers that were <hi>in the Church</hi> that was at <hi>Antioch:</hi> therefore theſe muſt needs be Teachers in another ſence then the reſt of the members there; and if ſo, then they were Teachers by office, and not by gift onely. Pardon me, if in uſing this diſtinction of Teachers by gift, and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by office, I hardly ſpeake ſence, for I muſt conforme my ſelfe to his lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is there not (in that very Chapter which he brings in one Verſe of to prove <hi>Sauls</hi> Preaching before called to the office of a Miniſter, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.) an expreſſe hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his call? even by a voyce from Heaven. If there needed any proofe in this matter, I could ſhew you how <hi>verſe</hi> 6. when <hi>Saul</hi> cried out, what wilt thou have me to doe? the Lord ſayes, <hi>Ariſe, and goe into the City, and it ſhall be told thee what thou muſt do,</hi> &amp;c. He ſends him to <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias,</hi> &amp; what <hi>Ananias</hi> by Viſion tels him, (though you have it not fully related in the ſame Chapter, yet) you have it from <hi>Sauls</hi> owne mouth in Chap. 22. verſ. 14,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150263:50"/>15. viz. That he was to goe to be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe unto the truth which was miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly given in to him. Was not this a ſufficient outward call? Yea more plain <hi>Acts</hi> 26.16, 17, 18, 19. where you finde that God himſelfe in that heavenly Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on told him, that he <hi>appeared to him to make him a Miniſter,</hi> verſ. 16. and that he did then <hi>ſend him,</hi> verſ. 17. And yet ſee, Ah! how often doth this fellow preſume to bring in <hi>Saul</hi> as Preaching before his call, to the office of a Miniſter, to make his matter good, although Scripture teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is ſo expreſſe againſt him.</p>
               <p>Beſides, <hi>Sauls</hi> Preaching was not in a conſtituted Church neither, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the leſſe to his purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Oh the confidence of men that can tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in ſuch heterogenious ſtuffe!</p>
               <p>But let us ſee whether the Scriptures thar are behind will prove any whit bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for his turne.</p>
               <p>He often urges 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10, 11, <hi>Every man as he hath received the Gift, ſo let him miniſter the ſame,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7. they may be ſpoken to both under one.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This is a very farre fetcht conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, Chriſtians muſt <hi>adminiſter their gifts:</hi> therefore they muſt be <hi>Publique Preachers.</hi> Is there no way in which a gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150263:51"/>Chriſtian can make uſe of his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, unleſſe he enter upon that work which God hath appointed men in office to doe? How many pretious ſouls (when this thing was never heard of) did in former times meet together, &amp; diſcourſe together of the things of God, making uſe of their gifts in comforting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inſtructing their children, families, friends, in ſuch a way as was convenient, and yet never dreamt of turning <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:</hi> though they knew they muſt <hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter their gifts.</hi> The <hi>P. G. Routed</hi> is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to ſee the ſoundneſſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between <hi>publique</hi> and <hi>private</hi> Preaching: Preaching taken in a large, and Preaching taken in a ſtrict ſence; which I proved before by two (I think) invincible Arguments. Take that diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction along with you, and you may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily anſwer what is pleaded from theſe Scriptures.</p>
               <p>But 2. Doth not this exhortation in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. extend to women, think you, as well as men? 'Tis in the Originall <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Every one.</hi> Muſt not women ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter their gifts as they have received? I have proved they muſt, from 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. compared with 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Acts</hi> 18.26. <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.1. and yet you know they
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150263:51"/>may not Preach <hi>publiquely</hi> in the Church.</p>
               <p>Wherefore the meaning of the two A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles can be no more but this, <hi>Let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one,</hi> as he is enabled, labour to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate good unto others, every one in his proper place, and capacity; if he have the ſtation of a private member, let him uſe his gifts, by brotherly advice, admonition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if he hath the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gift of Prophecy (for I ſhall prove Prophecy ſignifies an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gift) <hi>let him Prophecy.</hi> If he be called to be a <hi>Paſtour</hi> and <hi>Teacher,</hi> let him attend diligently on that: if a <hi>Deacon,</hi> let him follow that work faithfully: if a Ruling Elder, let him be diligent and upright in Ruling. Weigh the expreſſions well, with what I have ſaid, and tell me whether this be not the very direct ſcope of theſe two Scriptures now under examination: and if ſo, then alas what make they for his purpoſe? ſure nothing at all.</p>
               <p>A ſmall matter you ſee, will lead men that way which the ſtream of their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual pride carries them, or elſe theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures would not be taken for a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground for private Chriſtians to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the publique work of a Miniſter.</p>
               <p>He ſometimes comes in with that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.10, 11. <hi>All thy works ſhall praiſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:150263:52"/>thee, O Lord, and thy Saints ſhall bleſſe thee. They ſhall ſpeake of the glory of thy Kingdome, and talk of thy power.</hi> As though this hath any relation to publique Preaching, and not rather to thoſe Chriſtian duties of Prayer, Praiſe, and Diſcourſe, in which the Saints ſhall acknowledge God and the great things which he ha's done for them.</p>
               <p>There is but one Scripture more, and that is the conſtant place of refuge which he makes uſe of, when moſt put to it, and forced to ſpeak to his Queſtion, and that is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31. which, as he ſayes, proves gifted Brethrens liberty to Preach in a Church conſtituted: This I ſhall clear in a Diſcourſe by it ſelfe, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Prophecy,</hi> in the next place. In the meane while ſee how theſe men cry out for expreſſe Scripture, expreſſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, when the Queſtion is about any thing that croſſes their phanſie; and yet cry downe all for Antichriſtian, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the Spirit in the Saints, who withſtand ſuch things as they can bring no other Scripture for, then what indeed ſpeaks nothing at all to their purpoſe, being rightly underſtood: as you ſee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:150263:52"/>
               <head>That the gift of Prophecy which we read of in firſt times of the Goſpel Church, was extraordinary, and not as the <hi>P. G. Routed,</hi> ſayes, proper to all the Saints.</head>
               <p>I Reſolved to handle this by it ſelfe, and that ſomewhat largely, becauſe there is no one thing he doth ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon, as this, that Prophecying is an ordinary gift, and (as he ſayes) <hi>proper to all the Saints;</hi> and therefore, according to <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31. Chriſtians may <hi>all Propheſie, one by one.</hi> This then is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be cleared, that the gift of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy was extraordinary, and ſo ending with the Apoſtolicall times, when the Scriptures were perfected: which if I can doe, there will remaine nothing unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered of all he hath written for Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without Ordination, or an externall call to the Miniſteriall office.</p>
               <p>You may read, page 79. how that he brings in his Adverſary objecting, that the Prophets ſpoken of in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. were extraordinary, and you may obſerve it, he takes no notice of his Reaſons, but anſwers, <hi>I ſay they were not extraordinary,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:150263:53"/>but ordinary.</hi> A good anſwer, <hi>Ipſe dixit, Collier</hi> ſayes it. This puts me in mind of a ſtory I have heard of a Polemicall Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour that uſed in his Sermons to beat much upon Controverſies, &amp; once hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a difference between us and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, he cites <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and ſayes, <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> ſays ſo, but I ſay, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> thou lieft, and where is he now? So this man, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hall</hi> ſayes they were extraordinary, but I ſay, no, where is he now? If his teſtimony be infallible, then you may take it for a truth, which he ſo confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmes, but if we may beleeve Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture before him, I ſhall diſcover it to be falſe: and that, firſt anſwering his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and then laying downe mine owne.</p>
               <p>I will doe him ſo much right as to give you a view of all his ſtrength, not in one place onely, but in every place where he ſpeaks any thing argumentatively to this Queſtion, that nothing may goe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwered. I find five reaſons urged not all together, but ſome in one place, ſome in another; in page 60.81.83.87. I ſhall make reply to them in their order.</p>
               <p>His firſt Reaſon is in page 60. where he ſayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:150263:53"/>
                  <hi>Prophecying was an extraordinary gift in the time of the Law,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>but in the Goſpel dayes it is not ſo: becauſe it is to ſpeake edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, exhortation, and comfort.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.3. <hi>which is ordinary, and proper to all the Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſhall have ſome ſophiſtry from him, though but little good Logick.<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Prophets ſpeake to edification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore thoſe that ſpeak to edification are Prophets: This is his reaſoning. But I anſwer.</p>
               <p>This is a Fallacy which we call <hi>Falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia conſequentis,</hi> which is when one thinks conſequencies or propoſitions are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertible, and reciprocall when they are not. 'Tis true, ſuch as were <hi>Prophets</hi> did <hi>ſpeake to edification,</hi> &amp;c. But it followes not that if men <hi>ſpeake to edification,</hi> they are therefore <hi>Prophets.</hi> This is as if one ſhould argue thus, If it rained but now, the ground is wet; therfore if the ground be wet, it rained but now: a meer <hi>non ſequitur,</hi> for the ground may be wet ſome other way then by raine. Even ſo he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Prophets did ſpeak to edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he thinks he may conclude that if men ſpeak to edification they are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and ſo <hi>prophecy</hi> is ordinary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150263:54"/>
                  <hi>ſpeaking to edification</hi> is ſo. It follow not, for though Prophets ſpeak to edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, yet 'tis not that, but the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſpirit by which they ſpeak that denominates them Prophets.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas he ſayes <hi>[The Prophets under the Law were extraordinary, but theſe not, becauſe they did ſpeake to edification.]</hi> 'Tis very ſtrange, for is it not evident that the Prophets in the old Teſtament ſpake to edification alſo? To this he anſwers two things, page 83. for I will not paſſe over any thing of weight that he ſpeaks.</p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>This is more then the Scripture affirmes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it not ſtrange that this man ſhould have ſo much boldneſſe as to ſpeak thus?<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> He that will queſtion whether <hi>Amos, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea, Iſaiah,</hi> and the reſt of the Prophets did ſpeak to edification in their Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying, had need queſtion too whither thoſe Books that go under their names, and containe the ſum of their Prophecies, be indeed theirs or no; for is not the matter contained in thoſe Books for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification? Elſe what do we make with them in our Bibles? Ah filthy blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my! See what a bad cauſe will drive men to. But he adds,</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:150263:54"/>
2. <hi>If they did,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>they took not their denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Prophets from this kinde of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well fare a good confidence!<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> you may take his word for it if you will. If they were not denominated Prophets from this kinde of prophecying, from what kind of Prophecying then? Did they ever Prophecy except for edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Sure the man hath much forgot himſelfe. But for his learning: They were called Prophets, not from the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their Prophecies (which was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe) but from the manner of receiving the ſame from God by <hi>Inſpirations, Dreams</hi> and <hi>Viſions.</hi> See <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.6. <hi>If there be a Prophet among you, I the Lord will make my ſelfe knowne unto him in a Viſion, and will ſpeake unto him in a Dreame.</hi> Hence 'tis that Prophets were called <hi>Seers,</hi> 1 Sam. 9.9. <hi>For he that is now called a Prophet, was beforetime called a Seer.</hi> That is, ſuch a one as God reveales himſelfe unto by Viſion.</p>
               <p>This name is alſo given unto the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Prophets, in many places; as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.10. <hi>Amos</hi> 7.12. to ſhew us, that they were called <hi>Prophets</hi> as <hi>Seers, i. e.</hi> men to whom God appeared by <hi>Viſions,</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:150263:55"/>and <hi>extraordinary, inſpiration,</hi> not becauſe they <hi>foretold things to come,</hi> as he doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate. And this I prove alſo by the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Argument.</p>
               <p>That which did denominate their ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings <hi>Prophecies,</hi> did denominate them <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> that I hope will not be denied.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>extraordinary way of revelation</hi> did denominate their ſayings <hi>Prophecies.</hi> Therefore that did denominate them <hi>Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the <hi>extraordinary way of revelation</hi> did denominate their ſayings <hi>Prophecies,</hi> not this, that they did foretell things to come (as he intimates) is very evident, in that in Prophecying they ſpake not onely of things to come, but ſometimes of things paſt, ſometimes of things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. 'Tis true, the Prophets often ſpake of things to come, but not alwayes, and therefore they were not from thence cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Prophets. I ſhall make this yet more plaine to you by giving you forth a defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> that you may know what it is, and whence 'tis that men are called <hi>Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prophecy is a manifeſting by divine inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">What Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie is.</note> 
                  <hi>of hidden or ſecret things, whether paſt, preſent, or to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, a manifeſtation of <hi>hidden things,</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:150263:55"/>that is, of things that are not, or cannot be knowne or manifeſted any other way. 2. <hi>By Divine inſpiration,</hi> which is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way in which things ſecret and not revealed can be manifeſted. 3. I add, <hi>Whether the things be paſt, preſent, or to come,</hi> becauſe Prophecying is not onely of things future, but<note n="(a)" place="margin">Nec futura tantum praedicere eſt prophetare, ſed praeterita, &amp; praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia humanae ſcientiae, &amp; induſtriaeimpoſſibilia c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitu. <hi>Fl. Illyr. Cl. Ser. par. 1. p. 973.</hi>
                  </note> preſent, and paſt alſo. <hi>Moſes,</hi> he Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyed of the Creation of things unknowne to others. <hi>Eliſha</hi> by a Propheticall ſpirit diſcovered <hi>Gehazi's</hi> theft, 2 <hi>K.</hi> 5.25, 26. He diſcloſed the King of <hi>Syria's</hi> Counſell, and the preſent po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of his Army, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.8, 9. The Prophets often Propheſied of the preſent wickedneſſe of the people, as in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here you ſee is Prophecying of things paſt, and preſent, as well as things to come. So that the <hi>P. G. Routed</hi> is much miſtaken in the reaſon he gives why the Prophets in the time of the Law were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated, or called Prophets: 'Twas not becauſe they foretold things to come, as is proved, but becauſe they manifeſted to others (by Divine inſpiration) things that were ſecret and not knowne; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſt, preſent, or to come, it makes no difference. And obſerve too, in this
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150263:56"/>they ſpake to edification? as was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before) even as the Prophets ſpoken of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. are ſaid to do. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this reaſon alledged to prove the Prophets in the Goſpel dayes ordinary, is very frivolous and weak.</p>
               <p>If there were any difference betweene the Prophets before Chriſt, and thoſe in the Apoſtles time, it lay either in the clearneſſe of their Prophecies, one above the other, or elſe in this, that the inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the one was<note n="(b)" place="margin">Afflatus Apoſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non erat ſimilis af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flatui Prophetarum non enim erat ecſtaticus ſed compoſitus &amp; ſedatus, <hi>&amp;c. Cam. Tom. 3. p. 319.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taticall,</hi> and violent; and the other (ordinarily) more <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et</hi> and <hi>ſedate,</hi> viz. the inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Prophets ſpoken of in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. concerning whom 'tis ſaid, verſ. 32. <hi>The ſpirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi> That is<note n="(c)" place="margin">So <hi>Fl. Illyr.</hi> in his <hi>Cl. Script. Part</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 194. And <hi>Cam. Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 76. &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 461. Expound this place.</note> the Spirit of Prophecy was not ſo violent on them, but that they had power to containe themſelves, and to ſtay one for another, and ſo to ſpeak in order: Whereas uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally 'twas otherwiſe with the Prophets in the Old Teſtament, in whom the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration was many times ſo violent, that they could not take their owne time for Prophecying, as theſe in the New
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150263:56"/>Teſtament ordinarily could. But both had an extraordinary inſpiration of things ſecret, and not revealed and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted: from the which, both the one and the other, were denominated Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
               <p>Now if the <hi>P. G. Routed</hi> can bring me any in our dayes that are extraordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or immediatly inſpired by God unto the manifeſtation of things not revealed already, I will own them to be Prophets, and grant that they may Preach without any other call but their gift: but if there be none ſuch, then there are no Prophets, and ſo his allegation from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. is vain and impertinent.</p>
               <p>But I'le paſſe to his ſecond reaſon, to prove the gift of Propheſie ordinary, which is in the ſame place with the firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Teſtimony of Jeſus is the ſpirit of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> Revel. 19.10. <hi>But this is given to the brethren. Therefore,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Here is another Fallacy (I am afraid the Devil ha's plaid the Sophiſter with him,<note place="margin">Anſw. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and taught him to play the Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter with others) 'Tis that which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>A dicto ſecundum quid, ad dictum ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer,</hi> when a thing is ſaid to be <hi>ſimply</hi> ſo, or ſo; becauſe it is ſo onely <hi>in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:150263:57"/>The <hi>Teſtimony of Jeſus is the ſpirit of Prophecy,</hi> not <hi>ſimply,</hi> but as it is extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily inſpired into ſuch as do Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of Jeſus Chriſt, and of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: ſo conſidered, the teſtimony of Jeſus is the ſpirit of Propheſie. But now will it follow, the Blackmore is white in his teeth, therefore he is all white, or white, <hi>ſimpliciter,</hi> ſimply? No more will it follow, <hi>The Teſtimony of Jeſus</hi> (as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly and extraordinarily inſpired, and given in to ſuch as are <hi>Prophets</hi>) <hi>is the ſpirit of Prophecy;</hi> therefore the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Jeſus, ſimply conſidered as it is in all the Saints, is the ſpirit of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. This followes not.</p>
               <p>And leaſt any ſhould think I diſtinguiſh thus without any ground; you ſhall find in Chap. 1. verſ. 2. <hi>John</hi> himſelfe diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes between the <hi>word of God,</hi> and the <hi>Teſtimony of Jeſus,</hi> here called, <hi>The ſpirit of Prophecy.</hi> And verſ. 9. he ſayes, <hi>He was in the Iſle of Patmos for the word of God, and for the Teſtimony of Jeſus.</hi> That is (as ſome<note n="(d)" place="margin">Nempe relegarus fueratin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulam Patmon a Domitiano imperatore (uti fert hiſtoria Eccleſraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca) quod ſingularis, eſſet Evangelij dei praeco, quod<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſpiritu prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico actus Chriſto ſingulare redderet Teſtimonium. <hi>Lud. Cappel. Spic. p. 139.</hi>
                  </note> judicious men interpret) he was baniſhed there, for that he was a ſingular
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:150263:57"/>Preacher of the Goſpel, and not only ſo, but becauſe, being acted by a prophetical ſpirit, he gave a more ſingular teſtimony to Jeſus Chriſt, then other ordinary Preachers did. For this extraordinary teſtimony of Jeſus, which he had, together with other Prophets, was he baniſhed, and this is called the ſpirit of Propheſie.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſecondly I anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſw. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> that ſuch a teſtimony of Jeſus as is there ſpoken of, is the ſpirit of Propheſie, and no other: but in that place, not any Teſtimony of Jeſus is meant, but a ſpeciall kind of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony: that is evident, becauſe this clauſe <hi>[The Teſtimony of Jeſus is the ſpirit of Propheſie]</hi> is added to explaine what went before, that every one might underſtand what teſtimony of Jeſus the Angels meant. Sayes he, I meane by the Teſtimony of Jeſus, the ſpirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, not every kind of Teſtimony, but that which is the ſpirit of Propheſie. If this be not the ſence, this clauſe were needleſſe. Therefore it follows, that 'tis a ſpeciall kind of Teſtimony that is here intended, not ſuch as is in all the Saints. You will find if you examine the Text well, that indeed the intent of this clauſe which <hi>The</hi> P. <hi>G. Routed,</hi> urges, is not to ſignifie to us what the Teſtimony of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:150263:58"/>is conſidered ſimply in it ſelfe, but to ſignifie in what ſence it is uſed in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of the Verſe: So that it makes nothing at all to his purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Compare this <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.9. where the ſame ſpeech of the Angel, is ſet downe, though in other words, and 'twill help to make the ſence more clear.</p>
               <p>I have done with his ſecond Reaſon, let us try the third, and ſee whether 'twil prove any better: 'tis laid forth in this forme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every ſpirituall man is a Prophet. But the Saints are all ſpirituall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>therefore all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi> 1 Cor. 14.37. <hi>And by conſequence Prophecying is an ordinary gift.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis well concluded,<note place="margin">Anſw. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> if his firſt Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition were true. But he had need have a better Scripture for his purpoſe, to prove it, then that which he brings (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.37.) or elſe he muſt give me leave not to take it for true. The words are, <hi>If any man think himſelfe a Prophet, or ſpirituall, let him acknowledge, &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe 'tis ſaid, <hi>a Prophet or ſpirituall,</hi> therefore he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, <hi>Every ſpirituall man is a Prophet:</hi> How does this follow? May a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes in the ſame Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:150263:58"/>Chap. 5. ver. 11. <hi>If any brother be a fornicatour, or covetous;</hi> therefore every covetous man is a fornicatour? I hope not; but grant that [Spirituall] be an epithite given to <hi>Prophet,</hi> as I beleeve it is, yet all that can be concluded, is, that every Prophet is a ſpirituall man: And then, though every Prophet be a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all man, yet it will not follow, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſpirituall man is a Prophet, as he concludes, no more then it will follow, Every Gooſe is a living creature, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every living creature is a Gooſe. If this conſequence were good, then the <hi>P. G. Routed</hi> is a Gooſe too; and indeed he ſhewes himſelfe little better in this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He himſelfe ſayes, page 21. <hi>The Saints are not all Prophets,</hi> but the Saints are all <hi>ſpirituall.</hi> Therefore his Argument here, page 60. proves him a lier, page 21.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I anſwer; 'tis true, every one that is <hi>ſpirituall, i. e.</hi> having the extraordinary gifts of the <hi>Spirit</hi> mentioned before in that Chapter, is a Prophet, but if he takes <hi>[Spirituall]</hi> in that ſence, then the ſecond Propoſition of his Argument is falſe, for all the Saints are not ſpirituall in that ſence.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:150263:59"/>
You ſee what is become of his three firſt Reaſons, laid downe, page 60. There be two more yet behind, one in page 83. to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Prophets were ſuch as needed direction from the Apoſtle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>as to the manner and order of Prophecying, which if extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary they could rather have directed the Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am perſwaded this man hath lookt this 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. many times over,<note place="margin">Anſwer. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and yet can you think he ſhould never take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that the Apoſtle doth not onely give directions to the <hi>Prophets</hi> there, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes rules alſo to thoſe that <hi>ſpake in unknowne tongues?</hi> ver. 27, 28. And were not they extraordinarily inſpired unto that exerciſe, think you? He himſelfe doth in one place acknowledge it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis not ſtrange that <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould give direction to the Prophets, concerning the order and manner of Prophecying, though they were extraordinarily inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for you ſee he does give directions in the ſame place to ſome extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily inſpired with the gift of tongues: but he is unwilling to take notice of any thing that makes againſt him. Ah how
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:150263:59"/>are theſe men blinded with love to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty? They<note n="*" place="margin">They are drunk with errour, and ſo ſeldome walk ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtagger</hi> and <hi>reel</hi> near the truth many times, but cannot, or rather will not ſee it.</p>
               <p>But 2. I anſwer; theſe Prophets might be inſpired what to ſpeak,<note place="margin">Anſwer <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> but not in what manner and order. You know Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets infallibly guided in what they ſpake, were not alway infallibly guided in their actings, but therein might erre. Againe, all things are not revealed to one, God raiſed up many Prophets then, and what was not revealed to one was revealed to another. So that it might pleaſe the Lord that <hi>Paul</hi> (who had the ſpirit of Prophecy more then they all) ſhould have this among other things left to him, <hi>viz.</hi> to give directions to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prophets, as to the manner and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Prophecying.</p>
               <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Anſwer <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> This direction might be given by <hi>Paul</hi> (perhaps) not ſo much for their ſakes who were true Prophets ('tis like they would have kept to this order though <hi>Paul</hi> had never preſcribed it) but rather becauſe of ſome that might pretend a ſpirit of Prophecy, when not inſpired by God; and ſo bring in diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and confuſion into the Church: this ſeems to be intimated, <hi>verſ.</hi> 37.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:150263:60"/>
But he hath yet one reaſon more, which lies in page 87. in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Praying, and Prophecying are put together,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.5. <hi>was it extraordinary Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>I wonder that is left out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer;<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> I will put in that too <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his Learning, and prove there was an extraordinary gift of <hi>praying</hi> then, as well as an extraordinary gift of <hi>Prophecying.</hi> And indeed 'tis ſtrange, a man that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to ſo much acquaintance with Scripture as he does, ſhould never read of an extraordinary gift of <hi>praying,</hi> yea and <hi>ſinging</hi> too among the <hi>Corinthians:</hi> Pray read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.14, 15. <hi>For if I pray in an unknowne tongue, my ſpirit prayeth, but mine underſtanding is unfruitfull,</hi> &amp;c. What think you of this? is not here extraordinary <hi>praying?</hi> You may conjecture how theſe men read Scripture, if they did not rather ſtrive to bring Scripture to their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then their opinions to Scripture, theſe plain things could not be hid from them.</p>
               <p>You have had an account of the five Reaſons he gives to prove the gift of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie to be ordinary, and as he ſayes proper to all the Saints: you ſhall have as many of mine to prove the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:150263:60"/>
My firſt Reaſon is,<note place="margin">Reaſ. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe it is joyned in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. with gifts onely extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. Obſerve, that in this whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there are no gifts ſpoken of, but ſuch as are extraordinary, as ſpeaking in ſtrange languages, and interpretation of tongues, both which all acknowledge to be extraordinary: as for the firſt [ſtrange languages] they were uſed three wayes; in preaching, praying, and ſinging; all theſe extraordinary, and the Apoſtle puts in Prophecying among theſe, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of all promiſcuouſly, as gifts of the ſame kind, only differing in degrees of excellency, and yet ſhall we conceive that Prophecying is ordinary, when all the reſt that are intermixed in diſcourſe with it, are extraordinary? ſure 'tis very unlikely.</p>
               <p>Another paralel place is <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. where we find <hi>Prophets</hi> are ſet betweene two extraordinary officers, <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Evangeliſts. He gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts,</hi> &amp;c. Are <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> and <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> extraordinary? and yet <hi>Prophets</hi> (placed in order betweene them) ordinary? he muſt be a very eaſie and tractible ſoul that can beleeve it. But to this he anſwers ſomewhat, page 81. and 84. And what is it? Why, leaſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:150263:61"/>you ſhould think that Prophets were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, becauſe joyned with Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles that were ſo; he ſayes, that Apoſtles were not extraordinary neither (As for <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> he ha's nothing to ſay to them.) Ah alas! what is it that this man will not ſay to help a bad cauſe. Apoſtles were no Extraordinary officers he thinks if he put a good face upon it, 'twill paſſe.</p>
               <p>But what is his Reaſon? you have it page 84. <hi>Apoſtles</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>ſignifies <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſent.</hi> O profound reaſoning! Therefore all that are ſent are Apoſtles. And wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may not I ſay as well <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Angels fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies Meſſengers. There all Meſſenger are Angels. The Prophets of old were called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ſignifies <hi>Seers,</hi> or men ſeeing. Therefore all that ſee are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. I confeſſe this way they may be all Prophets, if they have not loſt their eyer. But if any man ſhould argue thus, would you not laugh at him? Would you not anſwer him? true, all that <hi>See</hi> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did, Divine and extraordinary Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, are indeed Prophets. Why ſo? pra<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> anſwer this man, that all that are <hi>Sent <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the Apoſtles were, by extraordinary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, and by an immediate call from God, and are guided to ſpeak infallibly
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:150263:61"/>as they were, are <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and none elſe: <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſuch I hope will be acknowledged to be extraordinary perſons, by all that are not extraordinary ſtupid.</p>
               <p>But he ſayes, <hi>Apoſtles are men ſent to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches,</hi> or to gather Saints, as his words are: why then, all that are ſent to gather Churches, are Apoſtles. What will he ſay of the <hi>ſeventy Diſciples,</hi> the <hi>ſeattered Brethren,</hi> were not they ſent to gather Saints? Or were they therefore all Apoſtles? I am ſure he argues very ſtifly, page 70. That they were not Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. An what confuſion is here? they were Apoſtles, and they were not Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: any thing for a ſhift.</p>
               <p>I would not ſo particularly diſcover his weakneſſe, and abſurdity, but that he deceives many with the opinion of much knowledge, when alas you may ſee he appears as very an Ignoramus, as ever, I think, was read in print.</p>
               <p>My ſecond Reaſon is,<note place="margin">Reaſ. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe this word <hi>Prophet</hi> ha's been alwayes uſed to ſignifie a perſon extraordinarily inſpired by God, when taken in a good ſence: and to ſignifie a <hi>Diviner,</hi> or a man of a familiar ſpirit, when taken in a bad ſence. I might bring at leaſt an hundred Texts to prove this, if 'twere needfull: but, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:150263:62"/>he ſayes Prophets under the Goſpel were not ſuch as they were that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law. I ſhall onely bring ſome Scriptures out of the New Teſtament, to prove that the Prophets were ſuch them too. As for <hi>Agabus,</hi> Act. 11.27. he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges he was extraordinary, becauſe as foretold things to come. But what with he ſay to <hi>Zecharias,</hi> Luke 1.22.67, &amp;c. <hi>Ananias,</hi> Act. 9.10. <hi>Cornelius,</hi> Act. 10.3. <hi>Peter,</hi> Act. 10.10.19. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.1. &amp;c. Act. 9. The Diſciples mentioned, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.6. Were not all theſe Prophet by extraordinary Viſion and Inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Doe not the Texts before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned make it plaine? I could give more inſtances, as in the Prophets that were at <hi>Antioch,</hi> to whom alſo God did ſpeak immediately, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.1, 2.</p>
               <p>Now if all theſe Prophets (which an more then we read of in all the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament beſide) were extraordinarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, and there be no reaſon in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture why we ſhould queſtion the like of the reſt; I hope we may conclude that Prophets even in the Goſpel dayes, were extraordinary alſo; and by conſequence that thoſe in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. were not ordinary, but ſuch as the reſt before mentioned.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:150263:62"/>
Will any man (unleſſe one that hath proſtituted his ſoul to Novelty) preſume to interpret a Scripture expreſſion in one or two places diverſly, from the conſtant acception of the ſame in all other places of Scripture where it is uſed, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny forcible reaſon? I beleive this conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence will hold, and appeare neceſſary. <hi>Prophet</hi> is conſtantly uſed in Scripture, to ſignifie one extraordinarily inſpired and gifted to teach; and there is no good reaſon why it may not ſignifie the ſame in 1 Cor. 14. Epheſ. 4.11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore it ſignifies one extraordinarily inſpired in thoſe places alſo.</p>
               <p>That the word <hi>Prophet</hi> is conſtantly uſed in Scripture to ſignifie one extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily inſpired, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I proved even now.</p>
               <p>Whether any good reaſon be given why it ſhould not ſignifie ſo in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. &amp;c. as well as in other places, you may judge by my anſwer to his reaſons before; if not, then you eaſily find the conſequence that will follow, <hi>viz.</hi> That the word Prophet as uſed in 1 Cor. 14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth ſignifie one extraordinarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired to teach, not an ordinarily gifted brother, as the P. G. Routed would have it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:150263:63"/>
My third Argument followes.<note place="margin">Reaſ. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>If the gift or ſpirit of Prophecy given out to the New Teſtament Prophets, be a fulfilling of that promiſe, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. then it is extraordinary, for that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſpeaks of extraordinary gifts, as appears by the plaine words thereof.</p>
               <p>But the gift or ſpirit of Prophecy gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out to the New Teſtament Prophets, is a fulfilling of that promiſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore it is extraordinary.</p>
               <p>All that I have to prove is the ſecond Propoſition, That the gift of Propheſie given out to the Prophets mentioned in the New Teſtament, is a fulfilling of that promiſe, <hi>Joel</hi> 2. And if any man doubt of this, let him look into <hi>Acts</hi> 2.16, 17. where the extraordinary gifts poured out on the Apoſtle there, are ſaid in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe termes to be a fulfilling of that promiſe. Now that could be a fulfilling of it onely in part; for the promiſe ſayes, <hi>Your ſons and your daughters ſhall Prophecy and ſee Viſions,</hi> &amp;c. Which can have relation to no other but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, both Men and Women, that were in the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> Act. 13.1. And the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> &amp; other Churches in thoſe dayes. Therefore they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Prophets.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:150263:63"/>
In the fourth place I argue thus.</p>
               <p>If Prophecying be ſet downe by the Apoſtle as diſtinct from ordinary teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Reaſ. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> then it is not the ſame with it, and ſo ordinary as that is.</p>
               <p>But Prophecying is ſet downe by the Apoſtle, as diſtinct from ordinary teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8.</p>
               <p>Therefore prophecying is not ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the ſame with ordinary teaching.</p>
               <p>There is nothing in this Argument that I can ſee needs any further proof.</p>
               <p>Fifthly,<note place="margin">Reaſ. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> It appears that this gift of prophecy was not ordinary, and (as he ſayes) <hi>proper to all the Saints,</hi> upon this reaſon, becauſe the gift of prophecy was given to others beſide the Saints, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not proper to them. Some had the gift of prophecy that had no ſaving grace in them, as you may gather from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1, 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22. <hi>John</hi> 11.50, 51. Now that which is given to others beſide Saints, is not proper to Saints. Neither can the ſpirit or gift of propheſie be the <hi>experimentall knowledge of Chriſt</hi> (as he ſayes) ſo as that every one that ha's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of Chriſt, and can ſpeak of it, is a Prophet: becauſe ſome you ſee, had indeed the gift of Propheſie, that never had any ſpirituall experience of Chriſt in their lives.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:150263:64"/>
Theſe are mine Arguments to prove that the gift of prophecy is extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; I could add more but that there is no need, the thing is ſo plaine.</p>
               <p>Now you may ſee what is become of his ſtrong <hi>Bulwarke,</hi> which he ſayes, <hi>all our wiſedome cannot undermine,</hi> page 79. 'Tis onely a Caſtle in the air, and ſo I leave it. Onely take notice, that I having ſufficiently proved that the gift of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, and the Prophets ſpoken of in the New Teſtament, were extraordinary, and ſpake by Viſion, and inſpiration; it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that all he brings to defend the preaching of gifted brethren, from the liberty of prophecying, is nothing to the purpoſe; unleſſe his gifted Brethren have extraordinary Viſions, or Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as the Prophets then had.</p>
               <p>I thinke I have now level'd all his ſtrong holds with the ground, and thou wilt not meet with any thing ſpoken to by him Argumentatively, but hath a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient anſwer in what I have writ. Some imputations, reproaches, ſlanders, rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, going along almoſt in every leaf, I ſhall leave to thy charity to confute, defiring in quietneſſe to paſſe them over.</p>
               <p>And although there be enough Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unanſwerably to prove the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:150263:64"/>of private-gifted-chriſtians preaching, among thoſe 20 laid downe by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hall</hi> in his <hi>Pulpit Guard:</hi> Yet ſhall I caſt in my mite after, conſiſting onely of four Arguments, and thoſe but very briefly touched upon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Same additionall Arguments, proving that all Gifted Brethren may not Preach, <hi>viz.</hi> as Gifted Brethren, not being appointed unto the Office, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>The Firſt Argument.</head>
                  <p>IF God hath not appointed and ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that all gifted brethren ſhould live of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> then all gifted brethren may not Preach the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>But God hath not ordained that all gifted brethren ſhould live of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>Therefore all gifted brethren may not Preach the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>The conſequence of my firſt propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which is that that I ſuppoſe will be denied) I prove by a plaine Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. where 'tis ſaid, <hi>Even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> The words need no Paraphraſe. God hath ordained
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:150263:65"/>that all thoſe that Preach the Goſpel, ſhould be maintained that way: if you may be publique Preachers, you may challenge a maintenance too: God ha's ordained you ſhould have it for Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 'tis evident in the Text.</p>
                  <p>But now as to the ſecond propoſition, that God ha's not ordained that all gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Brethren ſhould live of the Goſpel, that is, by a maintenance given them for Preaching of the Goſpel; I think it will not be denied. For if ſo be that a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance is to be given to all ſuch, then it muſt be provided by ſome body or other: now I would faine know by whom. All Chriſtians by his confeſſion are gifted more or leſſe to teach, now from whom ſhould their maintenance riſe, if but the greateſt part of them ſhould turn Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? Oh ſee this <hi>Babel</hi> and abhor it for ſhame: God does not ordaine things impoſſible.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>The Second Argument.</head>
                  <p>If to Preach publiquely be to exerciſe authority over others,<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> then none may Preach publiquely but ſuch as have Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall authority: which is not without the office.</p>
                  <p>But to Preach publiquely is to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:150263:65"/>Authority. Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt propoſition is undeniable.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond I prove by another plaine Scripture, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. where Women are forbidden to teach publiquely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they may not <hi>uſurp authority over the Man:</hi> Intimating, that to teach is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Authority over thoſe that are taught.</p>
                  <p>If any ſhould reply againſt the laſt clauſe of the firſt propoſition, that the gift beſtowed by God gives authority to the perſon, though the office be wanting. I anſwer, if the gift without the Office could give authority, then womens gifts would give them Authority too over the man; but that's not ſo: therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And here by the way you may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of another ground for the diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between publique and private Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Private teaching is no exerciſing of Authority, for women might doe that (as was proved formerly) who yet might not exerciſe Authority: Yea, and for a Chriſtian to give private admonition, advice, or reproof, to his brother, is no uſurping of Authority over him. But publique Preaching (as you ſee) is to exerciſe Authority.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:150263:66"/>
                  <head>The Third Argument.</head>
                  <p>If there be power in the Church to keep of Wolves,<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>i. e.</hi> falſe Teachers from the Sheep, then all that conceive they are gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, may not Preach till they are appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by ſuch as have power in the Church.</p>
                  <p>But the antecedent is undeniable.</p>
                  <p>Therefore the conſequent is ſo too.</p>
                  <p>The connexion of the antecedent and conſequent is unqueſtionable, for if men may Preach without being approved firſt by ſuch as have power in the Church, then (though they ſhould be Wolves) the Church have no power to keep them off. But they have power to keep ſuch off; read <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.20.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>The Fourth Argument.</head>
                  <p>If to appoint unto the office of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> and to the work of a Miniſter, be all one, then no man is appointed unto the work of a Miniſter (viz. Preaching) but he that is appointed to the office.</p>
                  <p>But to appoint to the office of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and to the worke of a Miniſter, is all one.</p>
                  <p>Therefore no man is appointed unto the work of a Miniſter (viz. Preaching) but he that is appointed to the office.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:150263:66"/>
The firſt propoſition he that ha's <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers</hi> impudence twice over cannot well queſtion.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond I ſhall prove by ſhewing you what it is to be appointed or ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the office of a Miniſter. And me thinks this ſhould be no very hard thing to underſtand, except unto ſuch as are not willing to ſee. He, you know, is ſaid to be appointed to ſuch or ſuch an office, who is (by ſuch as have power) entru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with, or commanded to the worke thereto belonging. So to be put into the Office of a Conſtable, is onely to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed (by ſuch as have power) to do the work of a Conſtable. And ſo it is in other offices. Now even ſo to be appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Office of a Miniſter, is to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with, and ſent forth to the work of a Miniſter, by ſuch as have power to doe the ſame. So that you ſee to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to the work, and to the office of a Miniſter, is the ſame: And therefore his diſtinction of <hi>Preachers by office,</hi> and Preachers by gift, without the office, (made uſe of ſo often by him) is meer non-ſence.</p>
                  <p>Now the power of ſending forth men to the work of the Miniſtry, is in God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, by Jeſus Chriſt. And he does the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:150263:67"/>ſame, either <hi>immediately,</hi> by himſelfe, <hi>viz.</hi> by Viſions and extraordinary inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and revelations: or <hi>mediately,</hi> by thoſe that have power in the Church. If therefore his gifted brethren be appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the work of the Miniſtry, neither <hi>immediately</hi> by God himſelfe, as before by extraordinary <hi>Viſion,</hi> &amp;c. as were the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> nor <hi>mediately,</hi> by ſuch as have power in the Church, then they have nothing to doe with the ſaid work: but if they put themſelves upon the ſame, that is verified in them that is ſpoken by the Prophet, <hi>They run, but I ſent them not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>If this be not plaine enough, 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no light in thee; or if any, yet covered over with ſuch a thick vail (I am afraid) of pride, or prejudice, as a divine power onely can remove. If thou ſee not this truth, all that I can doe more, is but to mourne in ſecret for thy blindneſſe.</p>
                  <p>I have done with this Queſtion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:150263:67"/>
               <head>His Seventh Error.</head>
               <head type="sub">That Humane Learning is no way ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary unto a Minister of the Goſpel, but that a man may Expound, and open the difficulties of Scripture, ſtop the mouths of Gain-ſayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as well without it as with it.</head>
               <p>THis he contends ſtifly for in page 38, 39, 41. Saying,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Power of the Spirit of Chriſt in Saints,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>is ſufficient to make men able to divide the word aright, to convince Gain-ſayers, to finde out the fullneſſe and emphaſis of the Originall,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now that you may not be deceived by his ambiguous termes,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> nor miſtake me in what I ſhall ſay, take a little direction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with you; for I love not to walk in the clouds of doubtfull expreſſions, as he does, whoſe deſigne is to cheat you.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. I doe not queſtion but the ſpirit of Chriſt is ſufficient to doe as he ſayes, if he pleaſed, for beſides that he is Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, we have examples in Scripture ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:150263:68"/>that he hath immediately ſupplied the want of humane Learning, by extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gifts of Tongues, and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of tongues. But the queſtion is not, whether the ſpirit be ſufficient, but, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Chriſtian (by the ſpirit, as now it works in the Saints) may be ſufficient unto theſe things, being not furniſhed in ſome meaſure with skill in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The Queſtion is not, whether or no the maine and principall Doctrine of the Scriptures be ſo plainly laid downe as that a Chriſtian may attaine unto the knowledge of the ſame without <hi>Humane learning,</hi> that is granted if he have a <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation</hi> (which cannot be but by the help of ſome that are learned) he may.</item>
               </list>
               <p>But the Queſtion is, whether the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis and fullneſſe of particular Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures can be found out, and the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of dark places opened, without theſe outward helps; or rather, whether a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Chriſtian, furniſhed with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall help of <hi>Learning,</hi> cannot bring forth more of the ſence and meaning of Scripture, and give a better accompt of the ſame, then another that ha's not <hi>Learning;</hi> if he can (which is that which we affirme) then <hi>Humane Learning</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:150263:68"/>unto one that will be a publique Preacher, and Expounder of Scripture: Though not abſolutely neceſſary, ſo as that where no learned men are, none may be Preachers: yet by a neceſſity of expediency, ſo as that ſuch as are learned onely are to be choſen to that work, if there be enough to be had. <hi>Learning</hi> is not neceſſary to make a Miniſter, but to make a Miniſter compleat.</p>
               <p>If you object (as he does) that the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>were not learned, yet compleat Miniſters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer; The Lord ſupplied in them the want of <hi>Humane acquired Learning,</hi> with the extraordinary gift of Tongues, and Interpretation of Tongues: 'Tis true, he found them unlearned, but he would not leave them ſo, when they were to be his Miniſters. If you conſider this well, it will make moſt againſt him of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing elſe. For, Obſerve it, God would not have thoſe that are imploied by him in ſuch a great work as the Miniſtry of the Goſpel is, to be deſtitute of <hi>Learning,</hi> no not <hi>Humane:</hi> for ſo was that which they had in a ſence, differing nothing from the gift of Tongues, and Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Tongues, that now is among us, but in this, that the one was <hi>immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:150263:69"/>inſpired,</hi> the other <hi>acquired</hi> by indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and ſtudy: both humane in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, becauſe converſant about that which is humane, <hi>viz.</hi> The Languages of ſeverall Nations. God ſaw it fit <hi>then</hi> that they ſhould not be without this part of Humane Learning, he ſaw it to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to compleat them for their worke, therefore much more is it requiſite <hi>now.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have the ſtate of the Queſtion, and me thinks the very ſtating of it makes the matter ſo plaine and out of doubt, that little needs to be ſpoken more to clear the ſame; for I think there is no man (that hath any ingenuity in him) but will acknowledge, that a ſpirituall Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that hath the help of humane Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is able to unfold more of Scripture, and do better to the clearing of the ſame, then another that hath not learning. But leaſt any man ſhould be ſo abſurd as to think otherwiſe (as <hi>The P. G. Routed</hi> does) I ſhall give a few inſtances for the proofe of the ſame among many more that might be brought.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:150263:69"/>
               <head>Some <hi>SCRIPTURES</hi> and Scripture-Expreſſions, a good account of which cannot be given, without the help of Humane Learning.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. THe <hi>P. G. Routed</hi> could not tell you that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, an Apoſtle, ſignifies one ſent (to clear a Scripture he ſpeaks to from miſtake, as he conceives) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out looking into the <hi>Originall,</hi> either with his owne eyes or ſome other mans. For I take it for granted that he will not ſay he knew <hi>Apoſtolos</hi> did ſignifie one ſent, by inſpiration. <hi>Ex ore ſuo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Out of his owne mouth ſhall he be condemned.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. You cannot give any reaſon why Chriſt ſhould ſay to <hi>Peter, Thou art Peter, and upon this Rock will I build my Church:</hi> unleſſe you be acquainted with the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, and ſo ſee the affinity (in ſound) of thoſe two words, <hi>Petros, Peter,</hi> and <hi>Petra,</hi> a Rock, which Chriſt had reſpect to in that ſpeech.</item>
                  <item>3. You can give no reaſon why, nor diſcover the myſtery that lies in this, that Our Mediatour is called <hi>Chriſt Jeſus, Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe without the Originall
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:150263:70"/>Languages, you know not what theſe names doe ſignifie.</item>
                  <item>4. In the 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. mention is made of ſome having a FORM of godlineſſe, but denying the power of it. And in <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. 'tis ſaid of Chriſt, that he was in the FORM of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Why may not one that denies the Divinity of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſay, the meaning of the latter Text is onely, that Chriſt was in the outward appearance of God, ſeing that in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer place the word FORM ſignifies only the outward ſhew and appearance? How can you withſtand this Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unleſſe you know that (though our Engliſh word be the ſame in both places, yet) the word uſed in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall in the former Scripture ſignifies onely the<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>outward ſhew or appearance;</hi> that uſed in the latter ſignifies the<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall forme</hi> of a thing.</item>
                  <item>5. How can any man give a rationall account of the meaning of that which we read, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.7, 8. unleſſe he be in ſome meaſure acquainted with the <hi>Jewiſh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities?</hi> where we are given to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the Body of the Jewiſh people were diſtinguiſhed into three ſorts. The<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Chaſidim, i. e.</hi> Good men. The<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Tſadikim, i.e.</hi> juſt or righteous men. And
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:150263:70"/>the<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Reſchangnim, i. e.</hi> wicked or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men, to which the Apoſtle ha's reſpect.</item>
                  <item>6. How will a gifted Brother with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Learning clear the difficulty that lies in that which is written in <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.23. compared with <hi>Luke</hi> 2.21? In the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer place it is ſaid (according to the Prophecy of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.14.) That <hi>Chriſts Name ſhould be called Emma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel:</hi> And in the latter place 'tis clear, that at his Circumciſion, when he came to be named, he was <hi>Named Jeſus.</hi> There is no ſalving of this ſeeming oppoſition, but by being acquainted with the Hebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme in the former place: for according to the Hebrews manner of ſpeaking, to be <hi>called</hi> ſignifies to <hi>be:</hi> and ſo it will conſiſt well enough with what is written in the latter Text. For he was to be <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> by the name <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and he was to <hi>be Emmanuel,</hi> i. e. <hi>God with us.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>An hundred more ſuch inſtances might I give you both in the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, of ſuch Scriptures as you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give a clear account of, but by the help of <hi>Learning,</hi> or by the help of ſuch as are <hi>Learned.</hi> But I think this is enough to demonſtrate his ignorance in ſaying, (without any reaſon, or any anſwer to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:150263:71"/>what is urged againſt him) that there is no uſe of Learning to the unfolding and clearing of Scripture, though I ſhould ſay no more.</p>
               <p>But there is yet one thing beſides, which I cannot paſſe over, page 41. ſpeaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the needfullneſſe of humane Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he quarrels with his Adverſary for uſing the word <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> asking deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly of him,<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>whether there be any ſuch word in all the Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> I know not what Scripture this man hath got, but in that which we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Scripture, the word is uſed neer an hundred times, even in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>But 2. It may be that he hath heard that the words in the Originall [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] ſignifie <hi>Holy Spirit.</hi> And how came he to know that, but by the help of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Learning? Though he hath little reaſon to except againſt the Engliſh tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of thoſe words. (Ghoſt and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit being all one, onely it may be the one a word more obſolete and out of uſe then the other) yet if it be true what his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception implies, that the Engliſh Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation is not exact in all points, then ſure there is need of Humane Learning to perfect it. For we had not the Engliſh
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:150263:71"/>Tranſlation at firſt without the help of the Learning of the Tranſlatours, nor can we have it mended but by the labour and help of ſuch as are Learned, that can look into the Original. And if ſo, is not <hi>Humane Learning</hi> neceſſary to an Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Scripture?</p>
               <p>There needs a wiſer man by far then I am to reconcile this man to himſelfe. He quarrels with Tranſlations as imperfect, and yet holds there is no need of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to rectifie them.</p>
               <p>But I have yet ſomewhat more to ſay before I leave this Queſtion. Seing the deſigne of ſuch men (as the <hi>P. G. Routed</hi>) is to deceive the ſimple with fair preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the honour of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and to make them beleeve that others (that oppoſe their corruptions) doe ſtrive to diminiſh and darken the glory of the operation of the Spirit of Chriſt in his Saints, that they may ſet up ſomwhat that is humane in the room of the ſame. I ſhall lay downe three or four Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or Notes, to give you ſome light in this thing, that you may know <hi>What is the work of the Spirit in revealing Truth to, or in the Saints.</hi> And <hi>How outward Humane helps to finde out the ſence of Scripture are conſiſtent with, and ſubſervient to the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:150263:72"/>
               <p n="1">1. I grant it to be an unqueſtionable truth, that no man is able without the ſweet and gracious operation of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of truth, <hi>ſavingly</hi> to underſtand and imbrace the myſteries of truth that are revealed in the Scriptures. <hi>The naturall man</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.) <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſſe unto him; neither can he know them becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi> That is, he cannot know them <hi>effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, ſavingly,</hi> he cannot know them as the ſpirituall man does, whoſe mind and heart is renewed through grace. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is not any Scripture under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by ſpirituall Chriſtians, the true Grammaticall ſence of which, a man that hath not the Spirit of Chriſt may not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine unto, by thoſe outward helps that are afforded to him. A <hi>notional</hi> knowledge of the ſence of Scripture, is common to naturall, as well as ſpirituall men. Elſe knowledge were an infallible Character of grace; which no body, I ſuppoſe, will affirme. So that,</p>
               <p n="3">3. (Obſerve it) That moſt bleſſed and heavenly work that the Lord Jeſus ha's to doe by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> in his Saints, is not ſo much to diſcover the <hi>Grammatical</hi> ſence
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:150263:72"/>of Scripture (which may be found out by ſuch as live much below Chriſt) as to bring home the ſence of Scripture cloſe to the heart, and to enlighten the mind to ſee the beauty and goodneſſe of that truth, that ſwims only in the brains of Naturall men. The work of the Spirit is to engrave truth upon the heart, to make our knowledge <hi>effectuall, practicall,</hi> and <hi>experimentall.</hi> Ah alas! many (I am afraid) are carried very high in the air of ſublime Angelicall Notions, upon the wings of ſuch a <hi>knowledge</hi> as the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>puffeth up,</hi> who are all the while ſtrangers to this worke of the Spirit, which is not to fill mens heads, but their hearts, with the truth.</p>
               <p>'Tis much to be ſuſpected, that ſuch as would make you beleeve that the work of the Spirit of grace, is to diſcover the ſence of Scripture, have never yet felt this ſaving work on their hearts. The Spirits work is not ſo low, and ordinary. If it were as theſe men would have it, why, then the work of the Spirit were only to make <hi>Notioniſts.</hi> Ah! let not Chriſtians be deceived; <hi>knowledge puffeth up, 'tis love edifies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Scripture is ſufficient to diſcover its owne ſence to all men diligently impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:150263:73"/>the outward helps afforded by God (though a ſanctified and ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſame, be communicated to none but through the Spirit) otherwiſe Scripture were no perfect rule, yea in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed no rule at all: For what is a Book or Waiting, without its meaning? 'Tis not the words or expreſſions, but the ſence of Scripture that is mans rule: if that be not viſible, we have no viſible rule, yea and if the Scriptures be given out in ſuch termes and expreſſions, as do not diſcover their owne meaning, what are they? or of what uſe? Beſides, if they doe not declare their owne meaning, but every one muſt fetch it from an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate work of the ſpirit, what were this but to make the Scripture a Noſe of Wax (as the Papiſts ſpeake) pliable to any ſence that the darkneſſe and vanity of mens minds will put upon it?</p>
               <p>Surely, he that denies a ſufficiency in Scripture to clear its owne meaning to one that uſes the outward means to that end afforded, denies Scripture to be any rule at all.</p>
               <p>But to make this plaine, ſuppoſe a Queſtion ariſe about the ſence or mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a particular Text; one ſayes this is the meaning, another that: which way
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:150263:73"/>will you go to decide the controverſie? Will you goe to the revelation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in you? Or to the letter of Scripture, arguing from the proper ſignification and uſe of ſuch words and expreſſions, as are in the Text diſputed of? If you have recourſe to the ſuppoſed revelation of the Spirit of Chriſt in you, why then the Scripture is not your rule: and how will you follow the Apoſtles advice, which is <hi>To try the ſpirits,</hi> &amp;c? If you have recourſe to the letter of Scripture, and argue from it, then Scripture ha's ſufficient in it to make out its owne ſence.</p>
               <p>Scripture, 'tis true, conteins in it an heavenly myſtery, <hi>that is hid from the wiſe and prudent.</hi> But what is the reaſon 'tis hid? <hi>Paul</hi> will tell you in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4. <hi>If our Goſpel be hid, 'tis hid to them that are loſt. In whom the God of this world hath blinded the minds of them which beleeve not,</hi> &amp;c. Mark the ground of this, that the <hi>Goſpel is hid,</hi> is becauſe they are <hi>blinded through unbeliefe.</hi> The Devil ruling in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men by fin and corruption, doth hinder them from giving hearty welcome unto the Truth. Queſtionleſſe the moſt of thoſe that heard <hi>Pauls</hi> Preaching, knew what he meant in his Sermons: and yet the Goſpel was hid to many of them:
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:150263:74"/>how ſo? why, they beleeved not: Their underſtandings and affections did not cloſe in with thoſe heavenly myſteries of Gods love which he did diſcover, ſo as to aſſent unto the reality of what was Taught, and to love, and delight in the ſame. The Goſpel is as a ſealed Book to naturall men, becauſe of the corruption that is in the heart, and in the mind, from whence it comes to paſſe that they cannot ſee the reality, beauty, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Scripture diſcoveries; 'tis not becauſe there is not plainneſſe enough in Scripture expreſſions, or becauſe the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel do not ſpeak plaine enough when they Preach Chriſt to them, but becauſe through corruption their minds are averſe from aſſenting to, and cloſing with the Truth.</p>
               <p>Now you muſt know that the work of the Spirit is to heale the underſtanding, and to ſanctifie and change the heart, and to make it pliable to the Truth; yea, and to ſtir up the whole man withall, unto a more diligent uſe of meanes of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: Thus the Spirit of Chriſt brings in truth unto the ſoul, and that ſo as it dwells and becomes fruitful in the heart, and in the converſation. This is a ſtep higher then the quainteſt Notioniſts of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:150263:74"/>our times deſire to be brought. If Truth were thus revealed in them, they would be more humble, more peaceable, more meek, then now they ſhew themſelves.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, I know not any truth in Scripture which a true Chriſtian hath an effectuall and practicall knowledge of by the Spirit, but a naturall man may know the ſame, onely his heart is not ſanctified through the Truth. Truth is not in him in power. The work of the ſpirit is to bring that into the heart, which by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward means and helps, may be brought into the head.</p>
               <p>Now then 4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. I honour I admire, I prize this bleſſed work of Jeſus Chriſt, by his Spirit in his Saints, revealing Truth in them. But this no way oppoſes the expediency and needfullneſſe of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward helps, to bring men to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of truth, which is that I plead for. The Spirit is pleaſed to make uſe of them, not that it elfe needs them, but becauſe we need them.</p>
               <p>The Spirit can communicate truth to ſouls without reading, hearing, medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet ſeing the Lord hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that he hath appointed theſe as the meanes that he will onely (in an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way) make effectuall to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:150263:75"/>of the ſoul; I hope 'tis no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to the Spirit of truth to ſay, that without theſe men cannot come to the knowledge of the Truth. Even ſo, the Spirit can by <hi>Extaticall Revelations,</hi> or an <hi>immediate inſpiration,</hi> give in truth unto the Preachers of the Goſpel now, as he did to the Prophets, and Pen-men of Scripture of old; but becauſe (as ha's been proved in confutation of the fourth Errour) God does not now reveal him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to any after that manner, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture rule being perfected; I hope it takes nothing from the honour of the Spirit to ſay, that the outward help of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is expedient, and needfull for a Miniſter of the Goſpel; and that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cannot be well opened and cleared without it.</p>
               <p>Alas! theſe men are miſtaken of the work of the Spirit, one part of which is (as I hinted before) to ſtir up ſouls un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a faithfull, diligent uſe of the outward means afforded for to lead them unto the knowledge of his mind in the word. The work of the Spirit is to ſtir up private Chriſtians to make uſe of the means they have, as Reading, Hearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to ſtir up Miniſters to make uſe of their helps, and to bring in to the ſervice of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:150263:75"/>Jeſus Chriſt in this great work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, all that knowledge both divine and humane, which they can attain unto. Not, as theſe men would have it, to caſt away as uſeleſſe all outward helps, and fit ſtill, waiting when knowledge will drop into their mouths, without any uſe of meanes.</p>
               <p>But you may ſmell what theſe men drive at.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. They are loath that any ſort of men ſhould be thought to have any thing more then themſelves.</item>
                  <item>2. They would faine have their owne ſpirits or phanſies to be the judge of the ſence of Scripture, that ſo their gloſſes on the ſame may goe for currant, though they have no affinity at all with the true Grammaticall ſence, and then his Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſhall be beſt, that ha's moſt bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and confidence in aſſerting it.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Oh the wantonneſſe and vanity of a proud heart! Let Chriſtians take heed.</p>
               <p>I have ſpoken I ſuppoſe ſufficiently to this matter.</p>
               <p>Whereas he ſayes,<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>The Spirit of Chriſt is enough to make men able Diſputants, ſuch as can convince gain-ſayers.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. You may ſee how true it is by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> who pretends to more gifts of the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:150263:76"/>Spirit then ordinary: If he can diſpute no better then he writes, I undertake that the meaneſt of the Romiſh Emiſſaries will eaſily argue him out of all his Religion.</item>
                  <item>2. How evident is it to every mans experience, that there are thouſands of precious ſoules that have the truth ſo deeply engraven upon their hearts, that all the powers of darkneſſe cannot take it from them; and yet are not able to maintaine it in diſpute againſt cunning oppoſers. Of which number was that Martyr that ſaid, <hi>I can die for Chriſt, though I cannot diſpute for him.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>But let this ſuffice you in ſhort as a defence of Humane Learning ſo much ſlighted.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe 'tis but a very ſmall portion of it (in compariſon of many of my Brethren) that I ever attained to, being ſoon taken off from the Univerſity, by the breaking forth of our Civil Wars. But as for that little which I have, I may ſay of it as <hi>Luther</hi> did of his skill in the Hebrew Language, <hi>I would not change it for all the riches in the World.</hi> Neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſhould I know what to doe in the Miniſtry without it. Though withall I muſt profeſſe too that God ha's been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gracious to me (I muſt ſpeak it to his
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:150263:76"/>praiſe) in bleſſing mine endeavours ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much upon the little ſtock I have. Unto which bleſſing eſpecially, I muſt attribute that ſufficiency I have unto my Miniſteriall duties.</p>
               <p>'Tis ſaid, <hi>Learning</hi> ha's never any adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to withſtand it, but <hi>Ignorance:</hi> I have ſo much learning as makes me ſee the worth and uſefullneſſe of Learning. And truly my experience of the ſame enforces me to ſpeak upon this ſubject (among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things) which I know the ſquea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh ſtomacks of many will not reliſh very well: However I ſhall take comfort in this, that I have done my duty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His Eighth Error.</head>
               <head type="sub">That the Ministry of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> is Antichristian.</head>
               <p>THis lies in the end of his Book, and I beleeve to perſwade men of this, is his end: Firſt in his intention, though laſt in execution. His deſigne is not ſo much to make more Preachers, as to vilifie thoſe that are already as <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> and no Miniſters.</p>
               <p>'Tis an heavy charge this that he brings
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:150263:77"/>in, not againſt ſome, but all Miniſters: I ſhall examine the ſtrength of what he urgeth to make it good.</p>
               <p>That which he ſpeaks is either in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to what is pleaded on their behalfe by his Adverſary: or elſe ſomething that he urgeth againſt them. I ſhall give you mine anſwer to every thing in its order; ſo as that you ſhall eaſily perceive that what he writes is grounded either on pittifull ignorance, or elſe on certaine ſlanderous, reproachfull, uncharitable calumnies, ſpringing out of his unſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, malicious ſpirit, in which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect to be beleeved by any, but ſuch as have made ſhip-wrack of love and godlineſſe, as he himſelfe (I am much afraid) ha's.</p>
               <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hal</hi> in his Book ha's ſix Arguments to prove that the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are not Antichriſtian: before I take off his anſwers to theſe Arguments, I ſhall reply to ſomewhat that he ha's to ſay againſt ſomething that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hall</hi> ſpeaks in Anſwer to an Objection, to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Authority of a Miniſter doth not depend on the perſons Ordaining, but principally on Chriſts inward call, diſcerned by gifts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We have our Ordination from Chriſt, by Biſhops, and Presbyters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:150263:77"/>
To this he gives anſwer in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You your ſelves have concluded the Biſhops Antichriſtian in their calling,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>and is yours Chriſtian? A Riddle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Did ever any of thoſe that have plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the uſurped power of <hi>Biſhops,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reply.</note> ſay that Biſhops are Antichriſtian ſimply conſidered? We all ſay their <hi>Lordly power</hi> which they aſſumed to themſelves over other Miniſters, was <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> not the Calling of Biſhops conſider it ſimply, as it ſignifies no other then the calling of a<note n="*" place="margin">Which is the true &amp; ancient ſence of the word <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </note> Paſtour or Elder. He might know if he were not willfully blind, that thoſe that have pleaded againſt the Lordly power of Biſhops, have conſtantly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the calling and office of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and a Paſtour, or Elder, are one and the ſame, and ſo that Power which they uſurped over their Brethren, was Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, and nothing elſe.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, he adds,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The outward calling you have from them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>and can they give you that they have not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? A Paradox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſhould have proved that the Biſhops had not the outward calling of Miniſters.<note place="margin">Reply.</note> Though Chriſt never called them to that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:150263:78"/>ſuperintendency over their fellow-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which they took to themſelves, yet he called many of them to the office of Miniſters, and in that reſpect they might ordaine and approve others to that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. This he ha's nothing to ſay to, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a confident dictate in the next page, in anſwer to this. That Biſhops were Miniſters, and Ordained, not as <hi>Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> but as <hi>Presbyters:</hi> To this he ſayes,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You juggle with the buſineſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Who knows not that not long ſince the name of Presbyter was a ſtranger among us, and to your ſelves too?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who knowes not?<note place="margin">Reply.</note> There is no man that is not as blind and ignorant as <hi>The P. G. Routed</hi> is, but knows that the name of <hi>Presbyter</hi> was ever as frequent among men of knowledge, as that of <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and knowne to be the name of Miniſters of the Goſpel, and ſo uſed, though his ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance makes him ſo bold as to ſay, we were ſtrangers to it. Hardly any that have written of the Miniſtry, but have uſed this name or title more or leſſe, to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Miniſters in office.</p>
               <p>So that we doe not new name <hi>Biſhops</hi> in calling them <hi>Presbyters</hi> (as he affirms) we give them their old name which they
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:150263:78"/>had before ever <hi>Lord Biſhops</hi> were known.</p>
               <p>'Tis knowne that in former ages of the Church, a Biſhop was onely as the Chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Elderſhip, not having any power over the reſt. Now as ſuch (not in reſpect of the additionall power, which by favour of Princes they got into) did they ordaine our Miniſters. This is no juggling (I hope) but plaine enough for any to underſtand.</p>
               <p>Whereas he ſayes,<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>Why is not Epiſcopos as good Scripture, as ancient, as honourable, as Presbyteros, an Elder?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, who ſayes but it is?<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we allow both the name and office of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> as he is the ſame with a <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Elder.</hi> But this he ſuggeſteth to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade his unwary Reader, that our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters do deny that they were Ordained by Biſhops as Biſhops; when as 'tis only denied that they were ordained by them as <hi>Lord Biſhops.</hi> If this be not a cheating trick to deceive the weak, let any man judge. But he adds.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If they were Miniſters and ſo ordained you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>you have done ill to Preach them downe as Antichriſtian. And ſo to lay them aſide as no Miniſters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who ever did ſo,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> unleſſe ſuch raſh ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:150263:79"/>as himſelfe? Is it not knowne that thoſe that were faithfull and godly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, have been, and ſtill are lookt upon as Miniſters? And do Preach Chriſt (and that too by appointment of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) in this Nation. I am ſure they did not long ſince<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. Hall, Dr. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher, <hi>&amp; others.</hi>
                  </note> and if not dead do yet; and yet ſee how impudently he vaunts upon this account <hi>[Where is your call from them now?]</hi> Notwithſtanding his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, thoſe Biſhops that were godly were never denied to be true Miniſters, though they were juſtly ſpoken againſt in reſpect of their uſurped power. They ſinned in taking that power to themſelves that Chriſt never gave them, but that did not make void that miniſteriall power which they had from Chriſt, by vertue of which, they ordained and appointed other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
               <p>Whereas 'tis moreover urged againſt him, <q>That the Power of the <hi>Presbytery</hi> is onely <hi>Miniſteriall,</hi> whereby it teſtifies, declares, and approves of thoſe whom God approves and calls.</q> This, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by his anſwer he doth not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and therefore I ſhall help him a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle according to my apprehenſion of it, becauſe indeed it makes very much to the clearing of this Queſtion. Wherefore take
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:150263:79"/>notice, that the Presbytery doe not give the Miniſters authority to him: That is from God, who appoints officer in his Church for the edification, and comfort thereof. The Presbytery do only teſtifie and declare (after they have proved and examined) that ſuch and ſuch are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and called of God: that ſo they may be Miniſters and in authority unto the <hi>Church,</hi> and may give themſelves to the work of the Miniſtry with more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, having ſuch a Seal to their Miſſion. Now it being ſo, that the <hi>authority and office</hi> deſcends to our Miniſters from Chriſt, and their Ordination by the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, is but <hi>their</hi> Miniſteriall teſtifying to the ſame; if that which is teſtified of our Miniſters be reall, and true (that is, if they be men that have an inward call from Chriſt) the corruption of thoſe that did approve and teſtifie, cannot at all make void their office. So that thoſe that are really gifted, and are faithfull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our Miniſters (for I plead only for ſuch) are true Miniſters of Chriſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome ſpots of Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme (if you will call it ſo) not then diſcovered to them, did ſtick upon thoſe that did teſtifie, declare, and appoint them to be Miniſters. For that blemiſh
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:150263:80"/>which ſtuck on the Ordainers, could no way redound to them that were Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained any further then they did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the ſame in them; and therefore now can redound nothing at all to ſuch as have condemned, and publiquely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt the ſame, as our faithfull Miniſters have done.</p>
               <p>This is a thing of ſpeciall note as to the clearing of the controverſie in hand; and though M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hall</hi> gives a ſufficient hint of it, yet <hi>The P. G. Routed</hi> paſſes it over as though he underſtood it not, when indeed I rather think 'tis becauſe he could not tell what to ſay to it.</p>
               <p>Onely you may find ſome of the froth of his unſanctified ſpirit ſwimming on the top of the 98<hi rend="sup">th</hi> page, which you muſt take as his anſwer in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If in ſome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                  <hi>pride, covetouſneſſe, ignorance, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, treachery, bloodthirſtineſſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in others, looſneſſe of life, prophaneneſſe, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, whoring,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>may delare men to be called of God: You</hi> (ſpeaking of the Miniſters of England) <hi>have ſo much to ſay for your ſelves as any people in the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is to perſwade,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and make the world beleeve that our Miniſters have no
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:150263:80"/>inward call from God. But how notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly falſe, and unchriſtian hell-borne a ſcandall this is (as applied by him) I leave to any modeſt Chriſtian to judge. I profeſſe it even makes mine heart trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to read him. He hopes if he can raile and revile roundly, ſome thing will ſticke, though all bee not beleeved. Is this chriſtianity?</p>
               <p>But let us ſee what he has to ſhew for an anſwer to the ſix Arguments urged to prove the validity of the Ordination of the miniſters of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>The Firſt Argument.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe whoſe Ordination was right for ſubſtance (though it fail in ſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance,<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> yet) is valid.</p>
                  <p>But the Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination was right for ſubſtance, in that they had the inward call, and the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward too, being examined for life, and learning; approved of, and ſet a party by prayer, exhortation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore their Ordination is valid, notwithſtanding ſome failing in circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantialls.</p>
                  <p>He denies not the firſt propoſition, it being indeed unqueſtionable: and againſt the ſecond he ſayes ſeverall things. <hi>As
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:150263:81"/>for the inward Call</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>That upon your owne account is no part of Ordination,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>and the ou<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>rd call came by ſucceſſion from Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the latter clauſe [<hi>The outward call came from Rome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reply.</note> &amp;c.] I will reply, when I come to anſwer his Reaſons to prove the Miniſtry of <hi>England</hi> Antichriſtian.</p>
                  <p>But as to the firſt <hi>[The inward call is no part of Ordination upon your owne account.]</hi> I anſwer; Do we ſay any ſuch thing? <hi>viz.</hi> That the inward call is no part of Ordination. Nay, do we not ſay on the contrary, that the inward call is the very life and ſoul of Ordination? What is this mans forehead made of, think you? 'Tis true, the inward call is no part of the outward Ordination, as the ſoul is no part of the body, but yet is in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and is an eſſentiall part of the man; even ſo this <hi>inward call</hi> is part of that compleat Ordination that makes a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; yea it makes that ordination which in reſpect of its externall part may be defective, and lame, to be for the maine, valid where it is: as the preſence of the ſoule in the body that is maimed, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſed, makes a true living man. Ah! this he would not have you ſee, if you do, then farewell to his whole cauſe.</p>
                  <p>But he hath ſom what more to ſay againſt this Argument, which is to this purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="153" facs="tcp:150263:81"/>
                     <hi>The inward call? ſay little of that.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> [intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that our miniſters have not the inward call] <hi>And the impoſition of hands, examination of life, and learning, prayer &amp;c. you ſo much boaſt of is nothing but an Antichriſtian forme without power; for neither they, nor you know what the gift, calling, or worke of the miniſtry of Chriſt is. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is his anſwer.<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> Now if any man can put ſo much confidence in him, as to take his word for this (when there is no proof of it yea when tis contrary to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unbiaſſed mans knowledge, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience) he may. But if you can but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve (as I thinke no modeſt chriſtian can chooſe but doe) 1 that thoſe many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of godly miniſters that are in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land have an inward call from God. 2. That impoſition of hands, examination and approbation, with prayer and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation are ſome thing beſides an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian forme: being commended in Scripture both by precept, and preſident. 3. That thoſe that did ordaine, and thoſe that were ordained, did any of them know what the gift, calling, or worke of a miniſter is, if you can (I ſay) beleeve any of theſe particulars, then (for ought is in his anſwer) hee gives you leave to
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:150263:82"/>conclude that our miniſters ordination is valid, and of force. And I deſire to leave the controverſy to the reader upon theſe termes too; for I thinke him not worthy to bee diſputed with, that hath ſo far made ſhipwrack of ingenuity and charity as to deny any of the particulars before mentioned. The 1. and 3. being ſo fully teſtified by experience, the 2. by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>The Second Argument.</head>
                  <p>The next Argument to prove the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of the Miniſtry (notwithſtanding it hath run downe to us through chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels ſomewhat impure) is the validity of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Arg. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> which hath come the ſame way to us.</p>
                  <p>Thus, if our Baptiſme be true Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, then our Miniſtry is a true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry.</p>
                  <p>But our baptiſme is true baptiſme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ergo.</p>
                  <p>Here he is glad he hath the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to ſpeake as bad of our Baptiſme as of our Miniſtry: for he denies both as Antichriſtian. Grant one abſurdity, and a thouſand will follow.</p>
                  <p>He ſayes;</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:150263:82"/>
                     <hi>You have now hit the nail upon the head,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> &amp;c. <hi>I deny either their or your Baptiſme to be any Baptiſme at all,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I anſwer 1.<note place="margin">Reply.</note> You muſt know this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument was never framed to convince an <hi>Anabaptiſt.</hi> There are others beſide Anabaptiſts that queſtion the validity of the Ordination of the Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and to them this Argument will prove unanſwerable. For if the Miniſtry (becauſe it came downe to us running a while through a dirty channell) be therefore null, then Baptiſme (which deſcended to us by the ſame way) muſt be null too. He that can deny that there is any Baptiſme or Baptized perſons in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Churches (whether Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or Presbyterian) of <hi>England, New-England, Scotland, France,</hi> &amp;c. will make light of this Argument: but it will make others, of more modeſt Principles, to be at a ſtand.</p>
                  <p>And here let me adviſe ſuch as (being no Anabaptiſts) doe yet conclude the Miniſtry of <hi>England</hi> no Miniſtry, and the Churches thereof no Churches, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine their Arguments well, and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the ſame Arguments may not be alſo proved as well that their owne Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:150263:83"/>is no Baptiſme. I am afraid they will find it ſo; and a hard task to anſwer the Anabaptiſts plea againſt them.</p>
                  <p>But to returne to my <hi>Router.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. He denies our Baptiſme as well as our Miniſtry, becauſe of its deſcending to us through the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But what will become of his Baptiſme then? If that be true which he confeſſes, page 97. <hi>That none can give that which he hath not himſelfe.</hi> None can ordaine a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter but he that is a Miniſter, and ſo none baptize but he that is baptized. How then is he or any of the Anabaptiſts in <hi>England,</hi> baptized? When 'tis knowne, that when they did ſet up their Dipping within theſe few years, two of them went down into the water, and one dipt the other, and ſo they the reſt. Could either of them be a baptized perſon by his owne rule? Sure 'tis time for him (by that time he hath well thought upon this) to deny his owne new Baptiſme, or to own ours. And if he owne our Baptiſme, then he muſt our Miniſtry too.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>The Third Argument.</head>
                  <p>If the Papiſts diſclaime our Miniſters as having no call from them,<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> then their calling cannot be Antichriſtian.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="157" facs="tcp:150263:83"/>
But they diſclaime our Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this he anſwers three things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>'Tis knowne, and your ſelves know, your Ordination came from thence.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is a bold falſhood, as I ſhall evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence more fully anon: never did any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> goe to <hi>Rome</hi> for Ordination. 'Tis true, in time of the firſt reformation begun by <hi>Luther,</hi> thoſe worthies that were ordained miniſters in the Church of Rome, according to the corrupt way of ordaning then in uſe, after they were made ſencible of the corruption, and witneſſed againſt it, and became inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of gathering out the pretious from the vile, were not againe ordained; but by vertue of what call they had, did ordaine others after a more pure and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular way; and have we our call from <hi>Rome</hi> and Antichriſt therefore? that is very ſtrange. But he adds,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They</hi> (viz the Papiſts) <hi>doe not ſay that your ordination in its riſe came not from them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>but in the preſent its not approved of by them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is alſo a falſe hood,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> as full of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance as the other is of boldneſſe. I
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:150263:84"/>beleeve he never read what any of them ſay as to this thing. 'Tis moſt evident that they doe flatly deny any ſucceſſion of our Miniſtry from theirs. And therefore call our Miniſters in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, and ſo downward<note n="*" place="margin">Scultingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Briſtous, Sanderus, Bellarmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> 
                     <hi>Miniſtros Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarios,</hi> and <hi>Miniſtros Reginales; Queen Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> and <hi>Parliament Miniſters.</hi> And they give the reaſon, <hi>Non a legitima conſecratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne aut inauguratione Catholica, ſed a Regina &amp; Parliamentis ſuam authoritatem ementitam derivant. i. e.</hi> They derive their fained authority not from lawfull conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or catholick inauguration, but from the <hi>Queen,</hi> and two houſes of <hi>Parliament.</hi> To this purpoſe ſpeak the Popiſh Writers mentioned in the margent with others; and yet doth not his ignorance make him ſo bold as to ſay, that the Papiſts doe not deny our miniſtery in its riſe to com from them? ſure theſe men thinke there is nothing true but what they know; when alas (poore ſoules) the Lord knowes they have but little to help them to know very much. But he adds in the third place.</p>
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>Grant by way of conceſſion that what you ſay were truth, yet is there but one Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt in the World?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="159" facs="tcp:150263:84"/>
This he ſayes to ſhew you,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> how our Miniſters may be Antichriſtian, though their Ordination came not from <hi>Rome:</hi> ſayes he, there are more Antichriſts then one.</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer; 1. See here he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to feare leaſt he ſhould not be able to make it good, that our Miniſters Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion came from <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore ſeeks a new ſtarting hole. <hi>There are more Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts then one:</hi> therefore they may be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian, though their Ordination came not from the Pope.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I confeſſe there are other. Antichriſts beſide the Pope; <hi>The P. G. Routed,</hi> and the men of his principles are Antichriſts, being againſt Chriſts Baptiſme, Miniſtry, Churches, if no more. But I hope our Miniſters had never Ordination from them, and therefore are not Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Beſide the <hi>Pope</hi> on the one hand who is <hi>Litterall Antichriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Familiſticall Enthuſiaſts</hi> of our times on the other hand, who are <hi>myſticall Antichriſts,</hi> I, for my part, know no notable Antichriſts in the World. If he had told what Antichriſt our Miniſters had their Ordination from, if not from the Pope, I ſhould have known what further reply to make; but now I muſt follow him in his anſwer to the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Argument.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:150263:85"/>
                  <head>The Fourth Argument.</head>
                  <p>If <hi>their</hi> Ordination be Antichriſtian, then cannot they with modeſty accuſe our Miniſters as Antichriſtian.<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>their</hi> Ordination is Antichriſtian, which is by the people, whereas Chriſts rule is, that Paſtors ſhould ordain Paſtors, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this he anſwers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A goodly Argument ſir!</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>as if becauſe ours is Antichriſtian, therefore yours may be ſo by a Law; Learned Logick!</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Oh the ſtupid ignorance of this fellow!<note place="margin">Reply.</note> was that the concluſion? The Argument concludes not that our Miniſters are not Antichriſtian, but that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> cannot with modeſty call them ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their owne Miniſtry is Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, being contrary to Chriſts rule. And that I hope is undeniable.</p>
                  <p>Whereas he goes on ſaying, that <hi>as to the Ordination mentioned (by the people) he knowes none ſuch:</hi> Truly I beleeve him, becauſe for the moſt part theſe men own no Ordination at all; but that Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they have (where they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) is by the people; as he confeſſes
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:150263:85"/>(if there be any ſence in the words that follow (but as yet I take them to be pure non-ſence, in a dreſſe of new words to deceive affectours of Novelty) if there be any ſence, I ſay, in what he goes on to ſpeak in this anſwer, it affirmes that their Ordination is by the people, and if ſuch an Ordination be good, how is it that page 97. he ſayes, 'tis a paradox to affirm that any one can give Ordination to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, that hath it not himſelfe? Sure the man ſeems to have a bad memory, or we ſhould not read ſuch groſſe contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Their Ordination is good though it be only by the people, and yet our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Ordination not good or valid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe that Ordained them were no Miniſters. If there be any reconciling of theſe two, then may we reconcile fire and water, light and darkneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>The Fifth Argument.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe Miniſters which are elected,<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> proved, ordained, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the mind of Chriſt, cannot be Antichriſtian.</p>
                  <p>But the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> now are ſo.</p>
                  <p>Therefore they cannot be Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
                  <p>To this he gives a three-fold anſwer,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:150263:86"/>to which I ſhall make reply in order.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Tour Minor I deny, you have no ſuch electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>becauſe you have no Church of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but profeſſing hypocrites.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This being an unchriſtian ſlander,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> need ſpeak nothing to it. If any man can think that all Churches, except Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, are but profeſſing hypocrites, I count him not worthy of an anſwer. He adds,</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>Thoſe Churches, ſuch as they are, never elected you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>This is a downeright falſhood,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> like much of the reſt of his Book; ſeeing (as 'tis well knowne) none are admitted to places, without a call from the people, or the better part of them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>You were</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>never proved,</hi> viz. <hi>of the knowledge of the Lord and his wayes, but of your Learning,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>This likewiſe is moſt untrue,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> and known to be ſo by all that are acquainted with the examination that ſuch as are ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned paſſe under; for when any one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents himſelfe to be Ordained, firſt of all Teſtimonialls under the hand of men of undoubted credit are required, to witnes
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:150263:86"/>to his blameleſſe converſation: when ſuch Teſtimonialls are produced, then is the perſon examined firſt concerning the <hi>work of grace on his heart,</hi> of which if he can give an account, he is then examined con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his skill in the Originall Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, his knowledge in the doctrine of the Goſpel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is proved by a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation on ſome controverſie in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that it may be knowne whether he can maintaine the truth againſt Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ayers. Then is he to Preach publiquely for the tryall of his gifts. And is here <hi>no proving of our knowledge of the Lord and his wayes?</hi> 'Tis ſtrange a man ſhould venture to publiſh to the world things ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently untrue.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>The Sixth Argument.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe Miniſters that are diametrically oppoſite to the Prieſts and ſhavelings of Antichriſt,<note place="margin">Arg. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> cannot be Antichriſtian.</p>
                  <p>But the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are ſo. Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this he anſwers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You are ſo in ſome circumſtantialls, not in the ſubſtance, for you owne their Miniſtry true,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>their Ordinances true,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What, doe we differ from them,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:150263:87"/>in circumſtantialls? Ah poor man! that can ſhift no better to helpe his bad cauſe. Are Juſtification by works, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images, praying to Saints, the Maſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but circumſtantialls? Sure hee'l prove himſelfe the beſt Advocate for <hi>Rome,</hi> if he can make this good, that the things we differ from them in, be onely circumſtantialls.</p>
                  <p>But 2. Is it not notoriouſly falſe, that we acknowledge their Church, Miniſtry, Ordinances, as true? What if <hi>Mr</hi> 
                     <hi>Hall</hi> in his ſecond Argument doe acknowledge that they <hi>were</hi> ſo? ſo does that famous worthy, <hi>Mr</hi> 
                     <hi>Burton,</hi> who loſt his ears un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Arch-Epiſcopall</hi> Tyranny, for the truth of Chriſt, in his anſwer to <hi>Mr</hi> 
                     <hi>Chom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley's</hi> defence of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> He grants they had the eſſence of a Church untill the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> but not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, when they were compleatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatized, and the faithfull had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from them. So doe we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge alſo; not that their Church and Miniſtry is true now.</p>
                  <p>There is yet one rub more which he labours to take out of his way. 'Tis ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that our miniſters doe convert ſouls, and therefore appear to be ſent of God, in that their Embaſſage is made ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full by God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="165" facs="tcp:150263:87"/>
To this he anſwers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If converſion be a proof of a Miniſter in office,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>then women may be Miniſters in office, or any man by whom God converts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Who but one of a <hi>womaniſh</hi> ſpirit and brain, would have given ſuch an anſwer?<note place="margin">Reply.</note> No man ſayes that converting ſoules, proves all miniſters in office that do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, but 'tis a proofe of the miniſtry of thoſe that doe officiate as miniſters, and in ſo doing convert. This is moſt evident by what <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2. If a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtian, making uſe of his Talents in his place, and within his ſphere, doe convert ſouls; this is a ſeal of Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving ſuch pious means as he uſes in order to the ſame. Even ſo if a man offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate as a miniſter in office, and God bleſſe his endeavours with the converſion of ſouls, 'tis a ſeal of his miſſion. And the reaſon is, becauſe God will not ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily concur with ſuch as he ſends not. Such as pretend unto an office from God, when he never gave them any, uſe not to have ſucceſſe given them by God in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing the ſame. God will not ſeal to a falſe and pretended miniſtry, by his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſame, as is plaine <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.21, 22. wherefore it is evident, that (ſeing the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:150263:88"/>Lord hath continually bleſſed the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of our Miniſters, with the converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many ſouls) our miniſters are the true miniſters of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But he ſayes, page 71.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In this likewiſe hath the Lord manifeſted his approving and calling the Preaching Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>the great number of converts from Antichriſtian, and Babiloniſh ignorance and confuſion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Converts?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> he means <hi>Anabaptiſticall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes,</hi> whom they have drawne away from holding any communion with the people of God in this Nation, or in any of the Churches of Chriſt in the world. A fine piece of Converſion indeed! Let him ſhew me any that have been brought off from a carnall, ſenſuall living, unto a reall and ſerious profeſſion of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of godlineſſe, by ſuch Preachers, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring as they do without being appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the office according to the rules of Chriſt; and he will ſhew more then ever I could find in all mine experience. I do not doubt but men really gifted, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring their gifts in a peaceable and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly manner, as becomes men in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate capacity, may have their endeavours bleſt with the Converſion of ſouls: but
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:150263:88"/>as for ſuch as goe beyond their line, and contentiouſly uſurp the miniſteriall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (as the <hi>P. G. Routed,</hi> and ſuch like travelling Preachers doe) well may they <hi>pervert</hi> many: I never found they <hi>conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> any.</p>
                  <p>That which he adds [That the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion our Miniſters boaſt of, is <hi>not a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion from ſin to God, but onely from ſin to reſting in duty.</hi>] It is ſuch a palpable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, and ſo big of envy, and pride, that I ſhall ſay nothing to it: Let Saints experiences ſpeak.</p>
                  <p>You have ſeen the invalidity and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his anſwers to thoſe ſix Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that prove our Miniſters free from Antichriſtianiſme: notwithſtanding what he alledges they firmely prove that which they are brought for, therefore I ſhall not add any more.</p>
                  <p>Onely in a word or two I ſhall exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the ſtrength of his Arguments to prove the affirmative, that they are Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mriſtian.</p>
                  <p>His Arguments as ſix in number, but onely one in weight, and that the firſt which is as followes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="168" facs="tcp:150263:89"/>
                     <hi>Thoſe Miniſters whoſe Ordination by ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on came from the authority of the Pope,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>are Antichriſtian.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But your Ordination by ſucceſſion came from the authority of the Pope, Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>This is his <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num magnum,</hi> which if I can anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> the controverſie will be at an end.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall firſt diſtinguiſh as to his firſt Propoſition, and ſo anſwer.</p>
                  <p>I would faine know what he means by <hi>[An Ordination comming by ſucceſſion from the Authority of the Pope.]</hi> the expreſſion is equivocall. Whether doth he meane, ſuch an Ordination as came by ſucceſſion from the Popes authority <hi>as the firſt Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of it?</hi> or elſe ſuch an Ordination as came from the Pope, onely by being conveyed downe to us through his hands?</p>
                  <p>If he meane the former, then I deny his ſecond Propoſition. The miniſters of <hi>England</hi> have not ſuch an Ordination as came by ſucceſſion from the Popes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, <hi>as the firſt Originall of it.</hi> For that Ordination which they have, as to its ſubſtance, was appointed by Jeſus Chriſt, and grounded on the Scriptures. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.10.4.14. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:150263:89"/>
If he meane the latter, then I deny his firſt Propoſition. For all miniſters are not Antichriſtian, that have ſuch an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination as (deſcending from Chriſt) ha's ſometime paſt through the Popes hand: for if ſo, then all that ha's paſt through his hands muſt be Antichriſtian: which if we grant, then not onely our miniſtry and baptiſme, but the <hi>Scriptures</hi> alſo muſt be Antichriſtian too. How will he help it? If he ſay the Scriptures came forth from Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo are recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; ſo ſay I, our Ordination came from Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo, under that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, our miniſters receive it. If he ſay, the Scriptures are received in their perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but the Ordination was vitiated and corrupted. I anſwer, the Scriptures alſo were very much corrupted by the Papiſts, as the Ordination was; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us hath been reſtored, by degrees, the beauty of both. Let him looke to himſelfe, the ſame door he goes out at, the ſame will I. If he can free the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from Antichriſtianiſme deſcending to us through the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the ſame way will I free the miniſtry and Ordination from Antichriſtianiſme, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it deſcended to us through the Pope; hands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="170" facs="tcp:150263:90"/>
But 2. Seing he is ſo particular in tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us when we had our Ordination from <hi>Rome,</hi> in the 99<hi rend="sup">th</hi> page. I ſhall ſpeak ſomewhat to the clearing of this alſo: he ſayes,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your Saint Auſtin the Monk being ſent from Rome to eſtabliſh the Romiſh faith in this Nation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                     <hi>he accordingly accompliſhing the worke, you have your Ordination by ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from thence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Very good: I am not very unwilling to grant him this.<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> Onely all the danger lies in theſe odious termes which hee makes uſe of, as <hi>Rome, Romiſh faith,</hi> and <hi>Auſtin the Monk;</hi> I ſhall diſcover his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand deceitfull dealing in uſing theſe expreſſions, and the matter will appeare as cleare as the Sun.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Whereas he ſayes, <hi>Auſtin</hi> came hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from <hi>[Rome]</hi> to eſtabliſh the <hi>[Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh faith]</hi> he ſpeaks deceitfully, or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly; for the <hi>Romiſh faith,</hi> was then the true, christian faith, and there was no Christian Church viſible on Earth but held communion with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (as then it was) in the ſame faith, for the maine.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was not the<note n="a" place="margin">Maſon de Min Angl. l. 2. cap. 4. Heyl. Geo. p. 469.</note> firſt that eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed the Chriſtian faith in <hi>England.</hi>
                     <pb n="171" facs="tcp:150263:90"/>This he is miſtaken in too. The Goſpel was received in <hi>England,</hi> long before <hi>Auſtin</hi> was. This Nation, that is now one Common-wealth; was anciently divided into ſeverall Kingdomes, ſome of them had received the faith long before <hi>Auſtins</hi> comming, if not by the means of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves (as ſome write) yet in the Apoſtolicall times by<note n="b" place="margin">Baronius, Capgravius</note> 
                     <hi>Joſeph of Arimathaea,</hi> and then afterward was the doctrine of Chriſt revived by<note n="c" place="margin">Maſon. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Heyl. p. <hi>469.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Eleutherius, Anno Dom.</hi> 180. which is 1471. yeares fince. At which time, I hope, the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were true miniſters, and the Church of Rome a true Church: more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over when <hi>Auſtin</hi> (that he ſpeakes of) came hither, which as<note n="d" place="margin">Beda. Epit. Hiſt. Angl Heyl. Geogr. p. 490.</note> hiſtory witneſſes, was about 1058. years ſince, there were ſeveral<note n="e" place="margin">Florebant apud illos eo ipſo tempore ſeptem E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi, &amp;c. <hi>Maſon. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum. Bed. L. 2. c. 2.</hi>
                     </note> Biſhops in <hi>England,</hi> profeſſing and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Chriſtian faith. So that if we go this way to work, our Miniſters Ordination will have an higher beginning then the <hi>Collier</hi> conceives. But if we doe grant that <hi>Auſtin</hi> (as he would have it) did firſt begin to ordaine Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters here (being ſent from <hi>Rome</hi>) and our Miniſters Ordination be from him: Yet that being (as you heard before) 1058. years agoe, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>
                     <pb n="172" facs="tcp:150263:91"/>was then alſo undoubtedly a true <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt. And<note n="f" place="margin">Vide obſecro an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſalem Epiſcopum ſe vocaret Gregorius, quod hodie Romae fit: An im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratorem Dominum ſuum jam vocaret Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifex qued fecit Grego rius. <hi>Maſon. de Min. Angl. L. 2. c. 4.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, then Biſh: of <hi>Rome,</hi> whom he (to affright and ſtartle ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people, calls <hi>Pope</hi>) was as farre from taking upon him that Antichriſtian power, that now the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> take to themſelves, as eaſt is from weſt. So that <hi>Auſtin</hi> and his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (that were appointed and ſent by this <hi>Gregory</hi> to eſtabliſh the Church of Chriſt in <hi>England,</hi> Baptizing ſuch as were added to the Church, and ſetting Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours over them) had a lawfull and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid miſſion (at leaſt for the maine) and therefore their Acts both of Baptizing, and Ordaining Miniſters, were valid alſo.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Whereas he ſtiles <hi>Auſtin,</hi> our <hi>[Saint Auſtin the Monk]</hi> 'tis either ignorantly, or deceitfully as before; for thoſe that were called <hi>Monachi,</hi> which we render <hi>Monks,</hi> in ſome of thoſe firſt hundred years after Chriſt, were as much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from thoſe idle gluttons, now in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> called <hi>Monks,</hi> as the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> then, are from the Popes now.<note place="margin">Divinis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. <hi>Maſon.</hi>
                     </note> The name ſignified, ſome wholly devoted to divine things; ſome wholly <hi>ſeparating themſelves unto the ſtudy of the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:150263:91"/>heavenly myſteries of truth.</hi> And ſo it was uſed then. 'Tis true, ſince the Apoſtaſie, this name is become odious by reaſon of thoſe ſwarms of luxurious idle belly-Gods, that are of that <hi>Order,</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> However, it was not ſo at firſt, nor at that time when <hi>Auſtin</hi> was ſent in this Nation. The<note n="g" place="margin">
                        <hi>Alſted. Parat. Theol. de Mon.</hi> Incredibile eſt quantum a majoribus ſuis degeneraverunt. <hi>Sayes an Ital. Papiſt.</hi>
                     </note> word then had a better acceptation and ſignification; and was taken up no doubt by pious men. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>P. G. Routed</hi> doth not deal plainly with his Reader (if he knew this, as I confeſſe I think he did not) in calling <hi>Auſtin a Monk</hi> in contempt; when as it was the wickedneſſe of after times that made this name contemptible and odious, that had before a better uſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Though <hi>Auſtin</hi> was a <hi>Monk</hi> before his miſſion into this Land, yet at his comming over he was Ordained a Biſhop<note n="h" place="margin">
                        <hi>Se</hi> Maſon. de Min. A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gl. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> c. 5.</note> either by the Biſhops of <hi>Germany</hi> (as <hi>Gregory</hi>) or elſe by the Biſhops of <hi>France</hi> (as <hi>Beda</hi>) writes: and ſo he ordained (with the help of others) thoſe Miniſters that were ordained here.</p>
                  <p>So that now ſee what is become of his great leading Argument, <hi>The Miniſters of England are Antichriſtian, becauſe their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination came from the Pope, by the meanes of
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:150263:92"/>Auſtin the Monk, who was ſent hither to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh the Romiſh faith.</hi> The Hiſtory being fully cleared up, it appears to be a meer bug-bear, and ſo far from making againſt our Miniſters, that it abundantly vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates them, and their Ordination. As for the truth of the relation, I have point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at ſome in the margent for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the ſame: And whoever is verſt in Hiſtory, knows it to be as certain as Hiſtory can make a thing; and that is as certaine as any thing is that we doe not ſee.</p>
                  <p>No man knowes that there was ſuch a one as <hi>Auſtin,</hi> or a Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> that ſent him hither, but by humane Hiſtory: and by the ſame know you that my rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this matter is true. I ſpeak to the weak.</p>
                  <p>As for his five other Arguments, they being nothing elſe but an heap of moſt malicious and wicked ſlanders: I ſhall ſay nothing to them.</p>
                  <p>He ſayes our Miniſters are Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; becauſe,
<list>
                        <item>1.<note place="margin">The P. G. Routed.</note> 
                           <hi>They doe not Chriſts worke.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>They deſire to ſit in Chriſts ſeat.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>They are belly-gods.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. <hi>They are enemies to the fellowſhip of the Saints.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="175" facs="tcp:150263:92"/>
                        <item>5. <hi>They ſet up ſomething like truth, in the roome of truth, in oppoſition to truth.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe are his five other Arguments to prove them Antichriſtian.<note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>This poyſonous froth thou mayeſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſcum off, if thou haſt but a little of the Spirit of the Goſpel in thee. I intend my Diſcourſe principally for honeſt hearts: wherefore, ſaying no more, I ſhall take my leave of <hi>The Pulpit Guard Routed,</hi> having I think, ſufficiently ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered his worthy, hoaſt of anſwers, and Arguments which he hath gathered up againſt Chriſt and the truth. I ſhall onely adviſe thee, <hi>Never credit boldnes more for this mans ſake.</hi> But ſeriouſly weigh all things in the ballance of the Sanctuary. <hi>Try all things, hold faſt that which is good.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:150263:93"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT-<hi>Advertiſement</hi> To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is another dangerous, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilent, blaſphemous Booke of this <hi>Colliers</hi> (againſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, yea and againſt the Perſon and Offices of Christ) which I did endeavour to get while I was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering this but could not. I know not whether he will make reply to this that I have written: Poſſible he may. 'Tis eaſie for a man to multiply Anſwers, if he take no care to ſpeake pertinently. If he ſhould Print another ſuch anſwer to me, as <hi>The Pulpit Guard Routed</hi> is to Mr <hi>Hall;</hi> I ſhall promiſe him never to take the pains to reply. Thou mayeſt well think he ſpake his beſt in anſwer
<pb facs="tcp:150263:93"/>to <hi>Mr Hall.</hi> and if that (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his boldnes, and confidence in writing) be ſo weak, abſurd, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, as thou mayeſt perceive by reading my reply: ſure if he ſhould put on double the confidence in writing another anſwer, I ſuſpect (and ſo mayeſt thou) 'twill be for ſtrength of Argument like the former; which if it be, I ſhall be coutent to ſuffer him to have the laſt word: suppoſing that none of thoſe (whoſe good I aim at) will count his cauſe beſt, that ſpeaks laſt.</p>
            <p>This, that is now ſwollen into a Treatiſe, was intended, at firſt, onely as a <hi>Monitorie Epiſtle,</hi> in two or three ſheets to ſtop the gangrene of his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours from ſpreading among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. I ut I met with ſuch variety of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities, ſo boldly and dangerouſly laid downe in his Diſcourſe to entrap the weake, that I could not well be ſhorter then I am.</p>
            <p>The Lord give thee underſtanding in all things.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:150263:94"/>
            <p>
               <hi>February</hi> 14. 1651.</p>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR, Edmund Calamy.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150263:94"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
